<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ben. Johnson's poems, elegies, paradoxes, and sonnets</title>
            <title>Selections. 1700</title>
            <author>King, Henry, 1592-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17230</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13155148</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13155148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 423:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ben. Johnson's poems, elegies, paradoxes, and sonnets</title>
                  <title>Selections. 1700</title>
                  <author>King, Henry, 1592-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 151, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by the booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Third issue of King's poems, with a spurious title, but without the additional elegies. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ben. Johnſon</hi>'s POEMS, ELEGIES, PARADOXES, AND SONNETS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:2"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHERS TO THE AUTHOR.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the common faſhion to make ſome addreſs to the Readers, but we are bold to direct ours to you, who will look on this publication with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which others muſt welcom into the world with Joy.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> comparing inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Authors to thoſe who had Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards ill neighboured, adviſed them to publiſh their own labours, leſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might ſteal the fruit: Had you followed his example, or liked the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, we had not thus treſpaſſed againſt
<pb facs="tcp:98172:3"/>your conſent, or been forced to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, which cannot but imply a faul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> committed. The beſt we can ſay fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves is, that if we have injured you it is meerly in your own defence preventing the preſent attempts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who to their theft would (by their falſe copies of theſe Poems) have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded violence, and ſome way have woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded your reputation.</p>
            <p>Having been long engaged on better contemplations, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps look down on theſe <hi>Juvenilia</hi> (moſt of them the iſſues of your youthful Mufe) with ſome diſdain; and yet the Courteous Reader may tell you with thanks, that they are not to be deſpiſed, being far from
<pb facs="tcp:98172:3"/>Abortive, nor to be diſowned, becauſe they are both Modeſt and Legitimate. And thus if we have offered you a view of your younger face, our hope is you will behold it with an unwrinkled brow, though we have preſented the Mirrour againſt your will.</p>
            <p>We confeſs our deſign hath been ſet forward by friends that honour you, who leſt the ill publiſhing might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure theſe things from whence you never expected addition to your credit (ſundry times endeavoured and by them defeated) furniſhed us with ſome papers which they thought Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; we may not turn their favour into an accuſation, and therefore give no intimation of their names, but
<pb facs="tcp:98172:4"/>wholly take the blame of this haſty and immethodical impreſſion upon our ſelves, being perſons at a diſtance, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are fitter to bear it then thoſe who are neerer related. In hope of your pardon we remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt devoted ſervants,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rich: Marriot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hen: Herringman.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98172:4"/>
            <head>POEMS.</head>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>
                  <hi>SONNET.</hi> The Double Rock.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SInce thou haſt view'd ſome Gorgon, and art grown</l>
                  <l>A ſolid ſtone:</l>
                  <l>To bring again to ſoftneſs thy hard heart</l>
                  <l>Is paſt my art.</l>
                  <l>Ice may relent to water in a thaw;</l>
                  <l>But ſtone made fleſh Loves Chymiſtey ne're ſaw.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore by thinking on thy hardneſs, I</l>
                  <l>Will petrify;</l>
                  <l>And ſo within our double Quarryes Wombe,</l>
                  <l>Dig our Loves Tombe.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſtrangely will our difference agree;</l>
                  <l>And, with our ſelves, amaze the world, to ſee</l>
                  <l>How both Revenge and Sympathy conſent</l>
                  <l>To make two Rocks each others Monument.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98172:5"/>
               <head>The Vow-Breaker.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen firſt the Magick of thine ey,</l>
                  <l>Uſurpt upon my liberty,</l>
                  <l>Triumphing in my hearts ſpoyl, thou</l>
                  <l>Didſt lock up thine in ſuch a vow;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When I prove falſe, may the bright day</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be govern'd by the Moons pale ray!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As I too well remember) This</l>
                  <l>Thou ſaid'ſt, and ſeald'ſt it with a kiſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Heavens! and could ſo ſoon that Ty</l>
                  <l>Relent in ſlack Apoſtacy?</l>
                  <l>Could all thy Oaths, and morgag'd truſt,</l>
                  <l>Vaniſh? like letters form'd in duſt</l>
                  <l>Which the next wind ſcatters. Take heed,</l>
                  <l>Take heed Revolter; know this deed</l>
                  <l>Hath wrong'd the world, which will fare worſe</l>
                  <l>By thy Example then thy Curſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hide that falſe Brow in miſts. Thy ſhame</l>
                  <l>Ne're ſee light more, but the dimme flame</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98172:5"/>Of funeral Lamps. Thus ſit and moane,</l>
                  <l>And learn to keep thy guilt at home.</l>
                  <l>Give it no vent; for if agen</l>
                  <l>Thy Love or Vowes betray more men,</l>
                  <l>At length (I fear) thy perjur'd breath</l>
                  <l>Will blow out day, and waken Death.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a Table-Book preſented to a Lady.</head>
               <l>VVHen your fair hand receives this little book</l>
               <l>You muſt not there for proſe or verſes look</l>
               <l>Thoſe empty regions which within you ſee,</l>
               <l>May by your ſelf planted and peopled be:</l>
               <l>And though we ſcarce allow your ſex to prove</l>
               <l>Writers (unleſs the Argument be Love);</l>
               <l>Yet without crime or envy you have roome</l>
               <l>Here, both the Scribe and Author to become.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98172:6"/>
               <head>To the ſame Lady upon Mr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Burtons</hi> Melancholy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IF in this Glaſs of Humours you do find</l>
                  <l>The Paſſions or diſeaſes of your mind,</l>
                  <l>Here without pain, you ſafely may endure,</l>
                  <l>Though not to ſuffer, yet to read your cure.</l>
                  <l>But if you nothing meet you can apply,</l>
                  <l>Then ere you need, you have a remedy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I do wiſh you never may have cauſe</l>
                  <l>To be adjudg'd by theſe fantaſtick Laws;</l>
                  <l>But that this books example may be known,</l>
                  <l>By others Melancholy, not your own.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Farewell.</hi> Splendidis longùm valedico nugis.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FArewell fond Love, under whoſe childiſh whip,</l>
                  <l>I have ſerv'd out a weary Prentiſhip;</l>
                  <l>Thou that haſt made me thy ſcorn'd property,</l>
                  <l>To dore on Rocks, but yielding Loves to fly:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98172:6"/>Go bane of my dear quiet and content,</l>
                  <l>Now practiſe on ſome other Patient.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farewell falſe Hope that fann'd my warm deſire</l>
                  <l>Till it had rais'd a wild unruly fire,</l>
                  <l>Which nor ſighs cool, nor tears extinguiſh can,</l>
                  <l>Although my eyes out-flow'd the Ocean:</l>
                  <l>Forth of my thoughts for ever, Thing of Air,</l>
                  <l>Begun in errour, finiſh't in deſpair.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farewell vain World, upon whoſe reſtleſs ſtage</l>
                  <l>Twixt Love and Hope I have foold out my age;</l>
                  <l>Henceforth ere ſue to thee for my redreſs,</l>
                  <l>Ile wooe the wind, or court the wilderneſs;</l>
                  <l>And buried from the dayes diſcovery,</l>
                  <l>Study a ſlow yet certain way to dy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My woful Monument ſhall be a Cell,</l>
                  <l>The murmur of the purling brook my knell;</l>
                  <l>My laſting Epitaph the Rock ſhall g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one:</l>
                  <l>Thus when ſad Lovers ask the weeping ſtone,</l>
                  <l>What wretched thing does in that Center lie?</l>
                  <l>The hollow Eccho will reply, 'twas I.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98172:7"/>
               <head>A Black-moor Maid wooing a fair Boy: ſent to the Author by Mr. <hi>Hen. Rainolds.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>STay lovely Boy, why fly'ſt thou mee</l>
               <l>That languiſh in theſe flames for thee?</l>
               <l>I'm black 'tis true: why ſo is Night,</l>
               <l>And Love doth in dark Shades delight.</l>
               <l>The whole World, do but cloſe thine eye,</l>
               <l>Will ſeem to thee as black as I;</l>
               <l>Or op't, and ſee what a black ſhade</l>
               <l>Is by thine own fair body made,</l>
               <l>That follows thee where e're thou go;</l>
               <l>(O who allow'd would not do ſo?)</l>
               <l>Let me for ever dwell ſo nigh,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt need no other ſhade than I.</l>
               <byline>Mr. <hi>Hen. Rainolds.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Boyes anſwer to the Blackmoor.</head>
               <l>BLack Maid, complain not that I fly,</l>
               <l>When Fate commands Antipathy:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98172:7"/>Prodigious might that union prove,</l>
               <l>Where Night and Day together move,</l>
               <l>And the conjunction of our lips</l>
               <l>Not kiſſes make, but an Eclipſe;</l>
               <l>In which the mixed black and white</l>
               <l>Portends more terrour than delight.</l>
               <l>Yet if my ſhadow thou wilt be,</l>
               <l>Enjoy thy deareſt wiſh: But ſee</l>
               <l>Thou take my ſhadowes property,</l>
               <l>That haſtes away when I come nigh:</l>
               <l>Elſe ſtay till death hath blinded mee,</l>
               <l>And then I will bequeath my ſelf to thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To a Friend upon <hi>Overbury's</hi> wife given to her.</head>
               <l>I Know no fitter ſubject for your view</l>
               <l>Then this, a meditation ripe for you,</l>
               <l>As you for it. Which when you read you'l ſee</l>
               <l>What kind of wife your ſelf will one day bee:</l>
               <l>Which happy day be neer you, and may this</l>
               <l>Remain with you as earneſt of my wiſh;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98172:8"/>When you ſo far lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e any, that you dare</l>
               <l>Venture your whole affection on his care,</l>
               <l>May he for whom you change your Virgin-life</l>
               <l>Prove good to you, and perfect as this Wife.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſame.</head>
               <l>Madam, who underſtands you well would ſwear,</l>
               <l>That you the Life, and this your Copie were.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To <hi>A. R.</hi> upon the ſame.</head>
               <l>NOt that I would inſtruct or tutor you</l>
               <l>What is a Wifes beheſt, or Husbands due,</l>
               <l>Gi;ve I this Widdow-Wife. Your early date</l>
               <l>Of knowledge makes ſuch Precepts ſlow and late.</l>
               <l>This book is but your glaſs, where you ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>What your ſelf are, what other Wives ſhould bee.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98172:8"/>
               <head>An Epitaph on Niobe turned to Stone.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis Pile thou ſeeſt built out of Fleſh, not Stone,</l>
                  <l>Contains no ſhroud within, nor mouldring bone:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This bloodleſs Trunk is deſtitute of Tombe</l>
                  <l>Which may the Soul-fled Manſion enwombe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſeeming Sepulchre (to tell the troth)</l>
                  <l>Is neither Tomb nor Body, and yet both.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a Braid of Hair in a Heart ſent by Mrs. <hi>E. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>IN this ſmall Character is ſent</l>
               <l>My Loves eternal Monument.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt we ſhall live, know, this chain'd Heart</l>
               <l>Is our affections counter-part.</l>
               <l>And if we never meet, think I</l>
               <l>Bequeath'd it as my Legacy.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98172:9"/>
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TEll me no more how fair ſhe is,</l>
                  <l>I have no minde to hear</l>
                  <l>The ſtory of that diſtant bliſs</l>
                  <l>I never ſhall come near:</l>
                  <l>By ſad experience I have found</l>
                  <l>That her perfection is my wound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And tell me not how fond I am</l>
                  <l>To tempt a daring Fate,</l>
                  <l>From whence no triumph ever came,</l>
                  <l>But to repent too late:</l>
                  <l>There is ſome hope ere long I may</l>
                  <l>In ſilence dote my ſelf away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ask no pity (Love) from thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor will thy juſtice blame,</l>
                  <l>So that thou wilt not envy mee</l>
                  <l>The glory of my flame:</l>
                  <l>Which crowns my heart when ere it dyes,</l>
                  <l>In that it falls her ſacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98172:9"/>
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <l>VVEre thy heart ſoft as thou art faire,</l>
               <l>Thou wer't a wonder paſt compare:</l>
               <l>But forzen Love and fierce diſdain</l>
               <l>By their extremes thy graces ſtain.</l>
               <l>Cold coyneſs quenches the ſtill fires</l>
               <l>Which glow in Lovers warm deſires;</l>
               <l>And ſcorn, like the quick Lightnings blaze,</l>
               <l>Darts death againſt affections gaze.</l>
               <l>O Heavens, what prodigy is this</l>
               <l>When Love in Beauty buried is!</l>
               <l>Or that dead pity thus ſhould be</l>
               <l>Tomb'd in a living cruelty.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GO thou that vainly do'ſt mine eyes invite</l>
                  <l>To taſte the ſofter comforts of the night,</l>
                  <l>And bid'ſt me cool the feaver of my brain,</l>
                  <l>In thoſe ſweet balmy dewes which ſlumber pain;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98172:10"/>Enjoy thine own peace in untroubled ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt my ſad thoughts eternal vigils keep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O could'ſt thou for a time change breaſts with me,</l>
                  <l>Thou in that broken Glaſs ſhouldſt plainly ſee,</l>
                  <l>A heart which waſtes in the ſlow ſmothring fire</l>
                  <l>Blown by deſpair, and fed by falſe deſire,</l>
                  <l>Can onely reap ſuch ſleeps as Sea-men have,</l>
                  <l>When fierce winds rock them on the foaming wave.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>SONNET. To Patience.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>DOwn ſtormy paſſions, down; no more</l>
                  <l>Let your rude waves invade the ſhore</l>
                  <l>Where bluſhing reaſon ſits and hides</l>
                  <l>Her from the fury of your tides.</l>
                  <l>Fit onely 'tis where you bear ſway</l>
                  <l>That Fools or Franticks do obey;</l>
                  <l>Since judgment, if it not reſiſts,</l>
                  <l>Will loſe it ſelf in your blind miſts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98172:10"/>
                  <l>Fall eaſie Patience, fall like reſt</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoft ſpells charm a troubled breaſt:</l>
                  <l>And where thoſe Rebels you eſpy,</l>
                  <l>O in your ſilken cordage tie</l>
                  <l>Their malice up! ſo ſhall I raiſe</l>
                  <l>Altars to thank your power, and praiſe</l>
                  <l>The ſoveraign vertue of your Balm,</l>
                  <l>Which cures a Tempeſt by a Calm.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>Silence. A SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PEace my hearts blab, be ever dumb,</l>
                  <l>Sorrowes ſpeak loud without a tongue:</l>
                  <l>And my perplexed thoughts forbear</l>
                  <l>To breath your ſelves in any ear:</l>
                  <l>Tis ſcarce a true or manly grief</l>
                  <l>Which gaddes abroad to find relief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was ever ſtomack that lackt meat</l>
                  <l>Nouriſht by what another eat?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98172:11"/>Can I beſtow it, or will woe</l>
                  <l>Forſake me when I bid it goe?</l>
                  <l>Then Ile believe a wounded breaſt</l>
                  <l>May heal by ſhrift, and purchaſe reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But if imparting it I do</l>
                  <l>Not eaſe my ſelf, but trouble two,</l>
                  <l>'Tis better I alone poſſeſs</l>
                  <l>My treaſure of unhappineſs:</l>
                  <l>Engroſſing that which is my own</l>
                  <l>No longer then it is unknown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If ſilence be a kind of death,</l>
                  <l>He kindles grief who gives it breath;</l>
                  <l>But let it rak't in embers lye,</l>
                  <l>On thine own hearth 'twill quickly dye;</l>
                  <l>And ſpight of fate, that very wombe</l>
                  <l>Which carries it, ſhall prove its tombe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Loves Harvest.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FOnd Lunatick forbear, why do'ſt thou ſue</l>
                  <l>For thy affections pay e're it is due?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98172:11"/>Loves fruits are legal uſe; and therefore may</l>
                  <l>Be onely taken on the marriage day.</l>
                  <l>Who for this intereſt too early call,</l>
                  <l>By that exaction loſe the Principall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then gather not thoſe immature delights,</l>
                  <l>Untill their riper Autumn the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> invites.</l>
                  <l>He that abortive Corn cuts off his ground,</l>
                  <l>No Husband but a Raviſher is found:</l>
                  <l>So thoſe that reap their love before they wed,</l>
                  <l>Do in effect but Cuckold their own Bed.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Forlorn Hope.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw long vain Hope do'ſt thou my joys ſuſpend?</l>
                  <l>Say! muſt my expectation know no end!</l>
                  <l>Thou waſt more kind unto the wandring Greek</l>
                  <l>Who did ten years his Wife and Country ſeek:</l>
                  <l>Ten lazy Winters in my glaſs are run,</l>
                  <l>Yet my thoughts travail ſeems but new begun.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooth Quick-ſand which the eaſy World beguiles,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou ſhalt not bury me in the falſe ſmiles.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98172:12"/>They that in hunting ſhadowes pleaſure take</l>
                  <l>May benefit of thy illuſion make.</l>
                  <l>Since thou haſt baniſht me from my content</l>
                  <l>I here pronounce thy finall baniſhment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farewell thou dream of nothing! thou meer voic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Get thee to fooles that can feed fat with noiſe:</l>
                  <l>Bid wretches markt for death look for reprieve,</l>
                  <l>Or men broke on the wheel perſwade to live.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth my comfort and beſt Hope ſhall be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſcorning Hope, nere to rely on thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Retreat.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PUrſue no more (my thoughts!) that falſe unkin</l>
                  <l>You may aſſoon impriſon the North-wind;</l>
                  <l>Or catch the Lightning as it leaps; or reach</l>
                  <l>The leading billow firſt ran down the breach;</l>
                  <l>Or undertake the flying clouds to track</l>
                  <l>In the ſame path they yeſterday did rack.</l>
                  <l>Then, like a Torch turn'd downward, let the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Deſire which nouriſht it, put out your flame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loe thus I doe divorce thee from my breſt,</l>
                  <l>Falſe to thy vow, and traitour to my reſt!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98172:12"/>Henceforth thy tears ſhall be (though thou repent)</l>
                  <l>Like pardons after execution ſent.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhalt thou ever my loves ſtory read,</l>
                  <l>But as ſome Epitaph of what is dead.</l>
                  <l>So may my hope on future bleſſings dwell,</l>
                  <l>As 'tis my firm reſolve and laſt farewell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TEll me you ſtars that our affections move,</l>
                  <l>Why made ye me that cruell one to love?</l>
                  <l>Why burnes my heart her ſcorned ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe breaſt is hard as Chryſtall, cold as Ice?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God of Deſire! if all thy Votaries</l>
                  <l>Thou thus repay, ſucceſſion will grow wiſe;</l>
                  <l>No ſighs for incenſe at thy Shrine ſhall ſmoke,</l>
                  <l>Thy Rites will be deſpis'd, thy Altars broke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O! or give her my flame to melt that ſnow</l>
                  <l>Which yet unthaw'd does on her boſome grow;</l>
                  <l>Or make me ice, and with her chryſtall chaines</l>
                  <l>Binde up all love within my frozen veines.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98172:13"/>
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Prethee turn that face away</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſplendour but benights my day.</l>
                  <l>Sad eyes like mine, and wounded hearts</l>
                  <l>Shun the bright rayes which beauty darts.</l>
                  <l>Unwelcome is the Sun that pries</l>
                  <l>Into thoſe ſhades where ſorrow lies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go ſhine on happy things. To me</l>
                  <l>That bleſſing is a miſerie:</l>
                  <l>Whom thy fierce Sun not warmes, but burnes,</l>
                  <l>Like that the ſooty Indian turnes.</l>
                  <l>Ile ſerve the night, and there confin'd</l>
                  <l>Wiſh thee leſs fair, or elſe more kind.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>DRy thoſe fair, thoſe chryſtal eyes</l>
                  <l>Which like growing fountains riſe</l>
                  <l>To drown their banks. Griefs ſullen brooks</l>
                  <l>Would better flow in furrow'd looks.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98172:13"/>Thy lovely face was never meant</l>
                  <l>To be the ſhoar of diſcontent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then clear thoſe watriſh ſtarres again</l>
                  <l>Which elſe portend a laſting rain;</l>
                  <l>Leſt the clouds which ſettle there</l>
                  <l>Prolong my Winter all the Year:</l>
                  <l>And the example others make</l>
                  <l>In love with ſorrow for thy ſake.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>SONNET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHen I entreat, either thou wilt not hear,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe my ſuit arriving at thy ear</l>
                  <l>Cools and dies there. A ſtrange extremitie</l>
                  <l>To freeze ith' Sun, and in the ſhade to frie.</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt all my blaſted hopes decline ſo ſoon,</l>
                  <l>Tis Evening with me, though at high Noon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For pity to thy ſelf, if not to me</l>
                  <l>Think time will raviſh, what I loſe, from thee.</l>
                  <l>If my ſcorcht heart wither through thy delay,</l>
                  <l>Thy beauty withers too. And ſwift decay</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98172:14"/>Arreſts thy Youth. So thou whil'ſt I am ſlighted</l>
                  <l>Wilt be too ſoon with age or ſorrow nighted.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To a Lady who ſent we a copy of verſes at my going to bed.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LAdy your art or wit could nere deviſe</l>
                  <l>To ſhame me more then in this nights ſurpriſe.</l>
                  <l>Why I am quite unready, and my eye</l>
                  <l>Now winking like my candle, doth deny</l>
                  <l>To guide my hand, if it had ought to write;</l>
                  <l>Nor can I make my drowſie ſenſe indite</l>
                  <l>Which by your verſes muſick (as a ſpell</l>
                  <l>Sent from the Sybellean Oracle)</l>
                  <l>Is charm'd and bound in wonder and delight,</l>
                  <l>Faſter then all the leaden chains of night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What pity is it then you ſhould ſo ill</l>
                  <l>Employ the bounty of your flowing quill,</l>
                  <l>As to expend on him your bedward thought,</l>
                  <l>Who can acknowledge that large love in nought</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98172:14"/>But this lean wiſh; that fate ſoon ſend you thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who may requite your rhimes with midnight proſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mean time, may all delights and pleaſing Theams</l>
                  <l>Like Maſquers revell in your M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>den dreams,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt dull to write, and to do more unmeet,</l>
                  <l>I, as the night invites me, fall aſleep.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Pink.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAir one, you did on me be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tow</l>
                  <l>Compariſons too ſweet to ow;</l>
                  <l>And but I found them ſent from you</l>
                  <l>I durſt not think they could be true.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But 'tis your uncontrolled power</l>
                  <l>Goddeſs-like to produce a flower,</l>
                  <l>And by your breath, without more ſeed,</l>
                  <l>Make that a Pink which was a Weed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Becauſe I would be loth to miſs</l>
                  <l>So ſweet a Metamorphoſis,</l>
                  <l>Upon what ſtalk ſoere I grow</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98172:15"/>Diſdain not you ſometimes to blow</l>
                  <l>And cheriſh by your Virgin eye</l>
                  <l>What in your frown would droop and die:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So ſhall my thankful leaf repay</l>
                  <l>Perfumed wiſhes every day:</l>
                  <l>And o're your fortune breathe a ſpell</l>
                  <l>Which may his obligation tell,</l>
                  <l>Who though he nought but ſhe can give</l>
                  <l>Muſt ever your (Sweet) creature live.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To his Friends of Christ-Church upon the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the Marriage of the Arts acted at Woodſtock.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BUt is it true, the Court miſlik't the Play,</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt Church and the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts have loſt the day;</l>
                  <l>That Ignoramus ſhould ſo far excell,</l>
                  <l>Their Hobby horſe from ours hath born the Bell?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Troth you are juſtly ſerv'd, that would preſent</l>
                  <l>Ought unto them, but ſhallow merriment;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98172:15"/>Or to your Marriage-table did admit</l>
                  <l>Gueſts that are ſtronger far in ſmell then wit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had ſome quaint Bawdry larded ev'ry Scene,</l>
                  <l>Some fawning Sycophant, or courted queane;</l>
                  <l>Had there appear'd ſome ſharp croſs-garter'd man</l>
                  <l>Whom their loud laugh might nick-name Puritan,</l>
                  <l>Cas'd up in factious breeches and ſmall ruffe,</l>
                  <l>That hates the ſurplis, and defies the cuffe:</l>
                  <l>Then ſure they would have given applauſe to crown</l>
                  <l>That which their ignorance did now cry down.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let me adviſe, when next you do beſtow</l>
                  <l>Your pains on men that do but little know,</l>
                  <l>You do no Chorus nor a Comment lack,</l>
                  <l>Which may expound and conſtrue ev'ry Act:</l>
                  <l>That it be ſhort and ſlight; for if 't be good</l>
                  <l>Tis long, and neither lik't nor underſtood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Know tis Court faſhion ſtill to diſcommend</l>
                  <l>All that which they want brain to comprehend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98172:16"/>
               <head>The Surrender.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY once dear Love; hapleſs that I no more</l>
                  <l>Muſt call thee ſo: the rich affections ſtore</l>
                  <l>That fed our hopes, lies now exhauſt and ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Like ſummes of treaſure unto Bankrupts lent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We that did nothing ſtudy but the way</l>
                  <l>To love each other, with which thoughts the day</l>
                  <l>Roſe with delight to us, and with them ſet,</l>
                  <l>Muſt learn the hateful Art how to forget.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We that did nothing wiſh that Heav'n could give</l>
                  <l>Beyond our ſelves, nor did deſire to live</l>
                  <l>Beyond that wiſh, all theſe now cancell muſt</l>
                  <l>As if not writ in faith, but words and duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet witneſs thoſe cleer vowes which Lovers make,</l>
                  <l>Witneſs the chaſt deſires that never brake</l>
                  <l>Into unruly heats; witneſs that breſt</l>
                  <l>Which in thy boſom anchor'd his whole reſt,</l>
                  <l>Tis no default in us, I dare acquite</l>
                  <l>Thy Maiden faith, thy purpoſe fair and white</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98172:16"/>
                  <l>As thy pure ſelf. Croſs Planets did envie</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to each other, and Heaven did untie</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> after then vowes could binde. O that the Starres,</l>
                  <l>When Lovers meet, ſhould ſtand oppos'd in warres!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since then ſome higher Deſtinies command,</l>
                  <l>Let us not ſtrive nor labour to withſtand</l>
                  <l>What is paſt help. The longeſt date of grief</l>
                  <l>Can never yield a hope of our relief;</l>
                  <l>And though we waſte our ſelves in moiſt laments,</l>
                  <l>Tears may drown us but not our diſcontents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fold back our arms, take home our fruitleſs loves</l>
                  <l>That muſt new fortunes trie, like Turtle Doves</l>
                  <l>Diſlodged from their haunts. We muſt in tears</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nwind a love knit up in many years.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n this laſt kiſs I here ſurrender thee</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ack to thy ſelf, ſo thou again art free.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hou in another, ſad as that, reſend</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he trueſt heart that Lover ere did lend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now turn from each. So fare our ſever'd hearts</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the divore't ſoul from her body parts.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98172:17"/>
               <head>The Legacy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>My deareſt Love! when thou and I muſt part,</l>
                  <l>And th'icy hand of death ſhall ſeize that heart</l>
                  <l>Which is all thine; within ſome ſpacious will</l>
                  <l>He leave no blanks for Legacies to fill:</l>
                  <l>Tis my ambition to die one of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who but himſelf hath nothing to diſpoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſince that is already thine, what need,</l>
                  <l>I to re-give it by ſome newer deed,</l>
                  <l>Yet take it once again. Free circumſtance</l>
                  <l>Does oft the value of mean things advance:</l>
                  <l>Who thus repeats what he bequeath'd before,</l>
                  <l>Proclaims his bounty richer then his ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But let me not upon my love beſtow</l>
                  <l>What is not worth the giving. I do ow</l>
                  <l>Somwhat to duſt: my bodies pamper'd care</l>
                  <l>Hungry corruption and the worm will ſhare.</l>
                  <l>That mouldring relick which in earth muſt lie</l>
                  <l>Would prove a gift of horrour to thine eie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98172:17"/>
                  <l>With this caſt ragge of my mortalitie</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et all my faults and errours buried he.</l>
                  <l>And as my ſear-cloth rots, ſo may kind fare</l>
                  <l>Thoſe worſt acts of my life incinerate.</l>
                  <l>He ſhall in ſtory fill a glorious room</l>
                  <l>Whoſe aſhes and whoſe ſins ſleep in one Tomb.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If now to my cold hearſe thou deign to bring</l>
                  <l>Some melting ſighs as thy laſt offering,</l>
                  <l>My peacefull exequies are crown'd. Nor ſhall</l>
                  <l>I ask more honour at my Funerall.</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt more richly balm me with thy tears</l>
                  <l>Then all the Nard fragrant Arabia bears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as the Paphian Queen by her griefs ſhow'r</l>
                  <l>Brought up her dead Loves Spirit in a flow'r:</l>
                  <l>So by thoſe precious drops rain'd from thine eies,</l>
                  <l>Out of my duſt, O may ſome vertue riſe!</l>
                  <l>And like thy better Genius thee attend,</l>
                  <l>Till thou in my dark Period ſhalt end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Laſtly, my conſtant truth let me commend</l>
                  <l>To him thou chooſeſt next to be thy friend.</l>
                  <l>For (witneſs all things good) I would not have</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98172:18"/>Thy Youth and Beauty married to my grave,</l>
                  <l>'Twould ſhew thou didſt repent the ſtyle of wife</l>
                  <l>Should'ſt thou relapſe into a ſingle life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They with prepoſterous grief the world delude</l>
                  <l>Who mourn for their loſt Mates in ſolitude;</l>
                  <l>Since Widdowhood more ſtrongly doth enforce</l>
                  <l>The much lamented lot of their divorce.</l>
                  <l>Themſelves then of their loſſes guilty are</l>
                  <l>Who may, yet will not ſuffer a repaire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe were Barbarian wives that did invent</l>
                  <l>Weeping to death at th'Husbands Monument,</l>
                  <l>But in more civil Rites She doth approve</l>
                  <l>Her firſt, who ventures on a ſecond Love;</l>
                  <l>For elſe it may be thought, if She refrain,</l>
                  <l>She ſped ſo ill Shee durſt not trie again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Up them my Love, and chooſe ſome worthler one</l>
                  <l>Who may ſupply my room when I am gone;</l>
                  <l>So will the ſtock of our affection thrive</l>
                  <l>No leſs in death, then were I ſtill alive.</l>
                  <l>And in my urne I ſhall rejoyce, that I</l>
                  <l>Am both Teſtatour thus and Legacie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98172:18"/>
               <head>The ſhort Wooing.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke an Oblation ſet before a Shrine,</l>
                  <l>Fair One! I offer up this heart of mine.</l>
                  <l>Whether the Saint accept my Gift or no,</l>
                  <l>He neither fear nor doubt before I know.</l>
                  <l>For he whoſe faint diſtruſt prevents reply,</l>
                  <l>Doth his own ſuits denial prophecy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your will the ſentence is; Who free as Fate</l>
                  <l>Can bid my love proceed, or elſe retreat.</l>
                  <l>And from ſhort views that verdict is decreed</l>
                  <l>Which ſeldom doth one audience exceed.</l>
                  <l>Love asks no dull probation, but like light</l>
                  <l>Conveyes his nimble influence at firſt ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I need not therefore importune or preſs;</l>
                  <l>This were t'extort unwilling happineſs:</l>
                  <l>And much againſt affection might I ſin:</l>
                  <l>To tire and weary what I ſeek to win.</l>
                  <l>Towns which by lingring ſiege enforced be</l>
                  <l>Oft make both ſides repent the victorie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98172:19"/>
                  <l>Be Miſtriſs of yourſelf: and let me thrive</l>
                  <l>Or ſuffer by your own prerogative.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtay, ſince you are Judge, who in one breath</l>
                  <l>Bear uncontrolled power of Life and Death,</l>
                  <l>Remember (Sweet) pity doth beſt become</l>
                  <l>Thoſe lips which muſt pronounce a Suitors doome</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I find that, my ſpark of chaſt deſire</l>
                  <l>Shall kindle into Hymens holy fire:</l>
                  <l>Elſe like ſad flowers will theſe verſes prove,</l>
                  <l>To ſtick the Coffin of rejected Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>St.</hi> Valentines day.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw that each feather'd Choriſter doth ſing</l>
                  <l>The glad approches of the welcome Spring</l>
                  <l>Now Phoebus darts forth his more early beam,</l>
                  <l>And dips it later in the curled ſtream,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould to cuſtome prove a retrograde</l>
                  <l>Did I ſtill dote upon my ſullen ſhade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oft have the ſeaſons finiſht and begun;</l>
                  <l>Dayes into Months, thoſe into years have run,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98172:19"/>Since my croſs Starres and inauſpicious fate</l>
                  <l>Doom'd me to linger here without my Mate:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loſs ere ſince befroſting my deſire,</l>
                  <l>Left me an Altar without Gift or Fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I therefore could have wiſht for your own ſake</l>
                  <l>That Fortune had deſign'd a nobler ſtake</l>
                  <l>For you to draw, then one whoſe fading day</l>
                  <l>Like to a dedicated Taper lay</l>
                  <l>Within a Tomb, and long burnt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Since nothing there ſaw better by the flame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſince you like your Chance, I muſt not try</l>
                  <l>To marre it through my incapacity.</l>
                  <l>I here make title to it, and proclaime</l>
                  <l>How much you honour me to wear my name;</l>
                  <l>Who can no form of gratitude deviſe,</l>
                  <l>But offer up my ſelf your ſacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hall then my worthy Lot! and may each Morn</l>
                  <l>Succeſſive ſprings of joy to you be born:</l>
                  <l>May your content ne're wane, untill my heart</l>
                  <l>Grown Bankrupt, wants good wiſhes to impart.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98172:20"/>Henceforth I need not make the duſt my Shrine,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſearch the Grave for my loſt Valentine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To his unconſtant Friend.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BUt ſay thou very woman, why to me</l>
                  <l>This fit of weakneſs and inconſtancie?</l>
                  <l>What forfeit have I made of word or vow,</l>
                  <l>That I am rack't on thy diſpleaſure now?</l>
                  <l>If I have done a fault I do not ſhame</l>
                  <l>To cite it from thy lips, give it a name:</l>
                  <l>I ask the banes, ſtand forth, and tell me why</l>
                  <l>We ſhould not in our wonted loves comply?</l>
                  <l>Did thy cloy'd appetite urge thee to trie</l>
                  <l>If any other man could love as I?</l>
                  <l>I ſee friends are like clothes, lad up whil'ſt new,</l>
                  <l>But after wearing caſt, though nere ſo true.</l>
                  <l>Or did thy fierce ambition long to make</l>
                  <l>Some Lover turn a martyr for thy ſake?</l>
                  <l>Thinking thy beauty had deſerv'd no name</l>
                  <l>Unleſs ſome one do periſh in that flame:</l>
                  <l>Upon whoſe loving duſt this ſentence lies,</l>
                  <l>Here's one was murther'd by his Miſtriſs eyes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98172:20"/>Or was't becauſe my love to thee was ſuch,</l>
                  <l>I could not chooſe but blab it? ſwear how much</l>
                  <l>I was thy ſlave, and doting let thee know,</l>
                  <l>I better could my ſelf then thee forgo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hearken ye men that ere ſhall love like me,</l>
                  <l>He give you counſel gratis: if you be</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt of what you like, let your fair friend</l>
                  <l>Lodge in your boſom, but no ſecrets ſend</l>
                  <l>To ſeek their lodging in a female breſt;</l>
                  <l>For ſo much is abated of your reſt.</l>
                  <l>The Steed that comes to underſtand his ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Growes wild, and caſts his manager at length:</l>
                  <l>And that tame Lover who unlocks his heart</l>
                  <l>Into his Miſtriſs, teaches her an art</l>
                  <l>To plague himſelf; ſhews her the ſecret way</l>
                  <l>How She may tyrannize another day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now my fair unkindneſs, thus to thee;</l>
                  <l>Mark how wiſe Paſſion and I agree:</l>
                  <l>Hear and be ſorry for't. I will not die</l>
                  <l>To expiate thy crime of levitie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> walk (not croſs-arm'd neither) ear, and live,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea live to pity thy neglect, not grieve</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98172:21"/>That thou art from thy faith and promiſe gone,</l>
                  <l>Nor envy him who by my loſs hath won.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt perceive thy changing Moon-like fits</l>
                  <l>Have not infected me, or turn'd my wits</l>
                  <l>To Lunacie. I do not mean to weep</l>
                  <l>When I ſhould eat, or ſigh when I ſhould ſleep;</l>
                  <l>I will not fall upon my pointed quill,</l>
                  <l>Bleed ink and Poems, or invention ſpill</l>
                  <l>To contrive Ballads, or weave Elegies</l>
                  <l>For Nurſes wearing when the infant cries.</l>
                  <l>Nor like th'enamour'd Triſtrams of the time,</l>
                  <l>Deſpair in proſe, and hang my ſelf in rhime.</l>
                  <l>Nor thither run upon my verſes feet,</l>
                  <l>Where I ſhall none but fools or mad-men meet,</l>
                  <l>Who mid'ſt the ſilent ſhades, and Myrtle walks,</l>
                  <l>Pule and do penance for their Miſtreſs faults.</l>
                  <l>I'm none of thoſe poetick male-contents</l>
                  <l>Born to make paper dear with my laments:</l>
                  <l>Or wild Orlando that will rail and vex,</l>
                  <l>And for thy ſake fall out with all the ſex.</l>
                  <l>No, I will love again, and ſeek a prize</l>
                  <l>That ſhall redeem me from thy poor deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>He court my fortune now in ſuch a ſhape</l>
                  <l>That will no faint die, nor ſtarv'd colour take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98172:21"/>
                  <l>Thus launch I off with triumph from thy ſhore,</l>
                  <l>To which my laſt farewell; for never more</l>
                  <l>Will I touch there. I put to Sea again</l>
                  <l>Blown with the churliſh wind of thy diſdain.</l>
                  <l>Nor will I ſtop this courſe till I have found</l>
                  <l>A Coaſt that yields ſafe harbour, and firm ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Smile ye Love-Starres; wing'd with deſire I fly,</l>
                  <l>To make my wiſhes full diſcovery:</l>
                  <l>Nor doubt I but for one that proves like you,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall find ten as fair, and yet more true.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Madam Gabrina, Or the Ill-favourd Choice. Con mala Muger el rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dio Mucha Tierra por el medio.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Have oft wondred why thou didſt elect</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſs of a ſtuff none could affect,</l>
                  <l>That wore his eyes in the right place. A thing</l>
                  <l>Made up, when Natures powers lay ſlumbering,</l>
                  <l>One, where all pregnant imperfections met</l>
                  <l>To make her ſexes ſcandal: Teeth of jet,</l>
                  <l>Hair dy'd in Orpment, from whoſe fretful hew</l>
                  <l>Canidia her higheſt Witch-crafts drew.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98172:22"/>A lip moſt thin and pale, but ſuch a mouth</l>
                  <l>Which like the Poles is ſtretched North and South.</l>
                  <l>A face ſo colour'd, and of ſuch a form,</l>
                  <l>As might defiance bid unto a ſtorm:</l>
                  <l>And the complexion of her ſallow hide</l>
                  <l>Like a wrack't body waſht up by the Tyde:</l>
                  <l>Eyes ſmall: a noſe ſo to her vizard glew'd</l>
                  <l>As if 'twould take a Planets altitude.</l>
                  <l>Laſt for her breath, 'tis ſomewhat like the ſmell</l>
                  <l>That does in Ember weeks on Fiſhſtreer dwell;</l>
                  <l>Or as a man ſhould faſting ſcent the Roſe</l>
                  <l>Which in the ſavoury Bear-garden growes.</l>
                  <l>If a Fox cures the Paralyticall,</l>
                  <l>Had'ſt thou ten Palſies, ſhe'd out-ſtink them all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I have found thy plot: ſure thou did'ſt trie</l>
                  <l>To put thy ſelf paſt hope of jealouſie:</l>
                  <l>And whil'ſt unlearned fools the ſenſes pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thou cur'ſt thy appetite by a diſeaſe;</l>
                  <l>As many uſe to kill an itch withall,</l>
                  <l>Quickſilver or ſome biting Minerall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dote upon handſome things each common man</l>
                  <l>With little ſtudy and leſs labour can;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98172:22"/>But to make love to a Deformity,</l>
                  <l>Onely commends thy great ability,</l>
                  <l>Who from hard-favour'd objects draw'ſt content,</l>
                  <l>As Eſtriches from iron nutriment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well take her, and like mounted George, in bed</l>
                  <l>Boldly atchieve thy Dragons Maiden-head:</l>
                  <l>Where (though ſcarce ſleep) thou mayſt reſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</l>
                  <l>None dares beguile thee of thy puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>The ſin were not more foul he ſhould commit,</l>
                  <l>Then is that She with whom he acted it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet take this comfort: when old age ſhall raze,</l>
                  <l>Or ſickneſs ruine many a good face,</l>
                  <l>Thy choice cannot impair; no cunning curſe</l>
                  <l>Can mend that night-peece, that is, make her worſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Defence.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Pienſan los Enamorados</l>
                     <l>Que tienen los otros, los oios quebranta dos.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHy ſlighreſt thou what I approve?</l>
                  <l>Thou art no Peer to try my love,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98172:23"/>Nor canſt diſcern where her form lyes,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thou ſaw'ſt her with my eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Say ſhe were foul and blacker than</l>
                  <l>The Night, or Sun-burnt African,</l>
                  <l>If lik't by me, tis I alone</l>
                  <l>Can make a beauty where was none;</l>
                  <l>For rated in my fancie, ſhe</l>
                  <l>Is ſo as ſhe appears to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But tis not feature, or a face,</l>
                  <l>That does my free election grace,</l>
                  <l>Nor is my liking onely led</l>
                  <l>By a well temperd white and red;</l>
                  <l>Could I enamour'd grow on thoſe,</l>
                  <l>The Lilly and the bluſhing Roſe</l>
                  <l>United in one ſtalk might be</l>
                  <l>As dear unto my thoughts as ſhe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I look farther, and do find</l>
                  <l>A richer beauty in her mind;</l>
                  <l>Where ſomething is ſo laſting fair,</l>
                  <l>As time or age cannot impair.</l>
                  <l>Had'ſt thou a perſpective ſo cleere,</l>
                  <l>Thou could'ſt behold my object there;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98172:23"/>When thou her vertues ſhould'ſt eſpy,</l>
                  <l>Theyl'd force thee to confeſs that I</l>
                  <l>Had cauſe to like her, and learn thence</l>
                  <l>To love by judgment not by ſence.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To One demarding why Wine ſparkles.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO Diamonds ſparkle, and thy Miſtriſs eyes;</l>
                  <l>When tis not Fire but light in either flyes.</l>
                  <l>Beauty not thaw'd by luſtful flames will ſhow</l>
                  <l>Like a fair mountain of unmelted ſnow:</l>
                  <l>Nor can the taſted vine more danger bring</l>
                  <l>Then water taken from the chryſtall Spring,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe end is to refreſh and cool that heat</l>
                  <l>Which unallayd becomes foul vices ſeat:</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thy boyling veins, mad with deſire</l>
                  <l>Of drink, convert the liquor into fire.</l>
                  <l>For then thou quaff'ſt down feavers, thy full bowles</l>
                  <l>Carouſe the burning draughts of Portia's coles.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If it do leap and ſparkle in the cup,</l>
                  <l>Twill ſink thy cares, and help invention up.</l>
                  <l>There never yet was Muſe or Poet known</l>
                  <l>Not dipt or drenched in this Helicon.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98172:24"/>But Tom! take heed thou uſe it with ſuch care</l>
                  <l>As Witches deal with their Familiar.</l>
                  <l>For if thy vertues circle not confine</l>
                  <l>And guard thee from the Furies rais'd by wine,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ten to one this dancing ſpirit may</l>
                  <l>A Devil prove to bear thy wits away;</l>
                  <l>And make thy glowing noſe a Map of Hell</l>
                  <l>Where Bacchus purple fumes like Meteors dwell.</l>
                  <l>Now think not theſe ſage moralls thee invire</l>
                  <l>To prove Carthuſian or ſtrict Rechabite;</l>
                  <l>Let fooles be mad, wiſe people may be free,</l>
                  <l>Though not to licenſe turn their libertie.</l>
                  <l>He that drinks wine for health, not for exceſs,</l>
                  <l>Nor drownes his temper in a drunkenneſs,</l>
                  <l>Shall feel no more the grapes unruly fate,</l>
                  <l>Then if he took ſome chilling Opiate.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>By occaſion of the Young Prince his happy birth</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AT this glad Triumph, when moſt Poets uſe</l>
                  <l>Their quill, I did not bridle up my Muſe</l>
                  <l>For ſloth or leſs devotion. I am one</l>
                  <l>That can well keep my Holy-dayes at home;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98172:24"/>That can the bleſſings of my King and State</l>
                  <l>Better in pray'r then poems gratulate;</l>
                  <l>And in their fortunes bear a loyal part,</l>
                  <l>Though I no bone-fires light but in my heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Truth is, when I receiv'd the firſt report</l>
                  <l>Of a new Starre riſen and ſeen at Court;</l>
                  <l>Though I felt joy enough to give a tongue</l>
                  <l>Unto a mute, yet duty ſtrook me dumb:</l>
                  <l>And thus ſurpriz'd by rumour, at firſt ſight</l>
                  <l>I held it ſome allegiance not to write.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For howere Children, unto thoſe that look</l>
                  <l>Their pedigree in God's, not the Church book,</l>
                  <l>Fair pledges are of that eternitie</l>
                  <l>Which Chriſtians poſſeſs not till they die;</l>
                  <l>Yet they appear view'd in that perſpective</l>
                  <l>Through which we look on men long ſince alive,</l>
                  <l>Like ſuccours in a Camp, ſent to make good</l>
                  <l>Their place that laſt upon the watches ſtood.</l>
                  <l>So that in age, or fate, each following birth</l>
                  <l>Doth ſet the Parent ſo much neerer earth:</l>
                  <l>And by this Grammar we our heirs may call</l>
                  <l>The ſmiling Preface to our funerall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98172:25"/>
                  <l>This ſadded my ſoft ſenſe, to think that he</l>
                  <l>Who now makes Lawes, ſhould by a bold decree</l>
                  <l>Be ſummon'd hence to make another room,</l>
                  <l>And change his Royal Palace for a tomb.</l>
                  <l>For none ere truly lov'd the preſent light,</l>
                  <l>But griev'd to ſee it rivall'd by the night:</l>
                  <l>And if't be ſin to wiſh that light extinct,</l>
                  <l>Sorrow may make it treaſon but to think't.</l>
                  <l>I know each male-content or giddy man,</l>
                  <l>In his religion with the Perſian,</l>
                  <l>Adores the riſing Sun; and his falſe view</l>
                  <l>Beſt likes not what is beſt, but what is new.</l>
                  <l>O that we could theſe gangrenes ſo prevent</l>
                  <l>(For our own bleſſing and their puniſhment)</l>
                  <l>That all ſuch might, who for wild changes thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Rack't on a hopeleſs expectation, burſt,</l>
                  <l>To ſee us fetter time, and by his ſtay</l>
                  <l>To a conſiſtence fix the flying day;</l>
                  <l>And in a Solſtice by our prayers made,</l>
                  <l>Reſcue our Sun from death or envies ſhade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But here we dally with fate, and in this</l>
                  <l>Stern Deſtiny mocks and controules our wiſh;</l>
                  <l>Informing us, if fathers ſhould remain</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98172:25"/>For ever here, children were born in vain;</l>
                  <l>And we in vain were Chriſtians, ſhould we</l>
                  <l>In this world dream of perpetuitie.</l>
                  <l>Decay is natures Kalendar; nor can</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t hurt the King to think he is a man;</l>
                  <l>Nor grieve, but comfort him, to hear us ſay</l>
                  <l>That his own children muſt his Scepter ſway.</l>
                  <l>Why ſlack I then to contribute a vote</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arge as the Kingdoms joy, free as my thought?</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong live the Prince, and in that title bear</l>
                  <l>The world long witneſs that the King is here:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay he grow up till all that good he reach</l>
                  <l>Which we can wiſh, or his Great Father teach:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et him ſhine long a mark to Land and Mayn,</l>
                  <l>Like that bright Spark plac't neereſt to <hi>Charles Wayn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd like him lead ſucceſſions golden Teame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich may poſſeſs the Brittiſh Diademe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But in the mean ſpace, let his Royal Sire,</l>
                  <l>Who warmes our hopes with true Promethean fire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o long his courſe in time and glory run,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill he eſtate his vertue on his ſon.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o in his Fathers dayes this happy One</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hall crowned be, yet not uſurp the Throne;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98172:26"/>And <hi>Charles</hi> reign ſtill, ſince thus himſelf will be</l>
                  <l>Heir to himſelf through all Poſteritie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Kings happy return from Scotland.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO breaks the day when the returning Sun</l>
                  <l>Hath newly through his Winter Tropick run,</l>
                  <l>As You (Great Sir!) in this regreſs come forth</l>
                  <l>From the remoter Climate of the North.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To tell You now what cares, what fears we paſt</l>
                  <l>What Clouds of ſorrow did the land ore-caſt,</l>
                  <l>Were loſt, but unto ſuch as have been there</l>
                  <l>Where the abſented Sun benights the year:</l>
                  <l>Or have thoſe Countreys traveld which nere feel</l>
                  <l>The warmth and vertue of his flaming wheel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How happy yet were we! that when you went,</l>
                  <l>You left within your Kingdomes firmament</l>
                  <l>A Partner-Light, whoſe luſtre may deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>The nightly glimm'ring Tapers of the skies,</l>
                  <l>Your peerleſs Queen; and at each hand a Starre</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hopeful beams from You enkindled are.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98172:26"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hough (to ſay truth) the light which they could bring</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erv'd but to lengthen out our evening.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heavens greater lampsillumine it; each ſpark</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dds onely this, to make the sky leſs dark.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay She who is the glory of her ſex</l>
                  <l>Did ſadly droop for lack of Your reflex:</l>
                  <l>Oft did She her fair brow in loneneſs ſhrowd,</l>
                  <l>And dimly ſhone, like Venus in a cloud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now are thoſe gloomy miſts dry'd up by You,</l>
                  <l>As the Worlds eye ſcatters the Ev'ning dew:</l>
                  <l>And You bring home that bleſſing to the land</l>
                  <l>Which abſence made us rightly underſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here may You henceforth ſtay! there need no charms</l>
                  <l>To hold You, but the circle of her arms,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fruitful love yields You a rich increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Seales of Your joy, and of the kingdomes peace.</l>
                  <l>O may thoſe precious pledges fixe You here,</l>
                  <l>And You grow old within that chryſtall Sphere!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pardon this bold detention. Elſe our love</l>
                  <l>Will meerly an officious trouble prove.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98172:27"/>Each buſie minute tells us as it flies,</l>
                  <l>That there are better objects for your eyes.</l>
                  <l>To them let us leave you, whil'ſt we go pray,</l>
                  <l>Raiſing this triumph to a Holy-day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And may that ſoul the Churches bleſſing want;</l>
                  <l>May his content be ſhort, his comforts ſcant,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Boſom-Altar does no incenſe burn,</l>
                  <l>In thankful ſacrifice for your return.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the Queen at Oxford.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GReat Lady! That thus quite againſt our uſe,</l>
                  <l>We ſpeak your welcome by an Engliſh Muſe,</l>
                  <l>And in a vulgar tongue our zeales contrive,</l>
                  <l>Is to confeſs your large prerogative,</l>
                  <l>Who have the pow'rful freedom to diſpenſe</l>
                  <l>With our ſtrict Rules, or Cuſtomes difference.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tis fit when ſuch a Star deigns to appeare</l>
                  <l>And ſhine within the Academick Spheare,</l>
                  <l>That ev'ry Colledge grac't by your reſort,</l>
                  <l>Should onely ſpeak the language of your Court;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98172:27"/>As if Apollo's learned Quire, but <hi>You</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No other <hi>Queen of the Aſcendent</hi> knew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let thoſe that liſt invoke the Delphian name,</l>
                  <l>To light their verſe, and quench their doting flame;</l>
                  <l>In Helicon it were High Treaſon now,</l>
                  <l>Did any to a feign'd Minerva bow;</l>
                  <l>When <hi>You</hi> are preſent, whoſe chaſt vertues ſtain</l>
                  <l>The vaunted glories of her Maiden brain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I would not flatter. May that dyet feed</l>
                  <l>Deform'd and vicious ſoules: they onely need</l>
                  <l>Such phyſick, who grown ſick of their decayes,</l>
                  <l>Are onely cur'd with ſurfets of falſe praiſe;</l>
                  <l>Like thoſe, who fall'n from Youth or Beauties grace,</l>
                  <l>Lay colours on which more bely the face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be You ſtill what You are; a glorious Theme</l>
                  <l>For Truth to crown. So when that Diademe</l>
                  <l>Which circles Your fair brow drops off, and time</l>
                  <l>Shall lift You to that pitch our prayers climbe;</l>
                  <l>Poſterity will plat a nobler wreath,</l>
                  <l>To crown Your fame and memory in death.</l>
                  <l>This is ſad truth and plain, which I might fear</l>
                  <l>Would ſcarce prove welcome to a Princes ear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98172:28"/>And hardly may you think that Writer wiſe</l>
                  <l>Who preaches there where he ſhould poetize;</l>
                  <l>Yet where ſo rich a bank of goodneſs is,</l>
                  <l>Triumphs and Feaſts admit ſuch thoughts as this;</l>
                  <l>Nor will your vertue from her Client turn,</l>
                  <l>Although he bring his tribute in an urn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Enough of this: who knowes not when to end</l>
                  <l>Needs muſt by tedious diligence offend.</l>
                  <l>'Tis not a Poets office to advance</l>
                  <l>The precious value of allegiance.</l>
                  <l>And leaſt of all the reſt do I affect</l>
                  <l>To word my duty in this dialect.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſervice lies a better way, whoſe tone</l>
                  <l>Is ſpirited by full devotion.</l>
                  <l>Thus whil'ſt I mention <hi>You, Your Royal Mate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Thoſe</hi> which your bleſt line perpetuate,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall ſuch votes of happineſs reherſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſofteſt accents will out-tongue my verſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98172:28"/>
               <head>A ſalutation of his Majeſties Ship the Soveraign.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MOve on thou floating Trophee built to fame!</l>
                  <l>And bid her trump ſpread thy Majeſtick name;</l>
                  <l>That the blew Tritons, and thoſe petty Gods</l>
                  <l>Which ſport themſelves upon the dancing floods,</l>
                  <l>May bow as to their <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ptune,</hi> when they feel</l>
                  <l>The awful preſſure of thy potent keel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great wonder of the time! whoſe form unites,</l>
                  <l>In one aſpect two warring oppoſites,</l>
                  <l>Delight and horrour; and in them portends</l>
                  <l>Diff'ring events both to thy foes and friends</l>
                  <l>To theſe thy radiant brow, Peaces bright Shrine,</l>
                  <l>Doth like that golden Conſtellation ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Which guides the Sea man with auſpicious beams,</l>
                  <l>Safe and unſhipwrackt through the troubled ſtreams,</l>
                  <l>But, as a blazing Meteor, to thoſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t doth oftents of blood and death diſcloſe.</l>
                  <l>For thy rich Decks lighten like Heavens fires,</l>
                  <l>To uſher forth the thunder of thy Thes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98172:29"/>
                  <l>O never may croſs wind, or ſwelling wave</l>
                  <l>Conſpire to make the treach'rous ſands thy grave:</l>
                  <l>Nor envious rocks in their white foamy laugh</l>
                  <l>Rejoyce to wear thy loſſes Epitaph.</l>
                  <l>But may the ſmootheſt, moſt ſucceſsful gales</l>
                  <l>Diſtend thy ſheet, and wing thy flying ſailes:</l>
                  <l>That all deſignes which muſt on thee embark,</l>
                  <l>May be ſecurely plac't as in the Ark.</l>
                  <l>May'ſt thou, where ere thy ſtreamers ſhall diſplay,</l>
                  <l>Enforce the bold diſputers to obey:</l>
                  <l>That they whoſe pens are ſharper then their ſwords:</l>
                  <l>May yield in fact what they deny'd in words.</l>
                  <l>Thus when th'amazed world our Seas ſhall ſee</l>
                  <l>Shut from Uſurpers, to their own Lord free,</l>
                  <l>Thou may'ſt returning from the conquer'd Main,</l>
                  <l>With thine own Triumphs be crown'd <hi>Soveraign.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98172:29"/>
               <head>AN EPITAPH On his moſt honoured Friend Richard Earl of Dorſet.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt no profane ignoble foot tread neer</l>
                  <l>This hall ow'd peece of earth, <hi>Dorſet lies here.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A ſmall ſad relique of a noble ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>Free as the air, and ample as his merit;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe leaſt perfection was large, and great</l>
                  <l>Enough to make a common man compleat.</l>
                  <l>A ſoul refin'd and cull'd from many men,</l>
                  <l>That reconcil'd the ſword unto the pen,</l>
                  <l>Uſing both well. No proud forgetting Lord,</l>
                  <l>But mindful of mean names and of his word.</l>
                  <l>One that did love for honour, not for ends,</l>
                  <l>And had the nobleſt way of making friends</l>
                  <l>By loving firſt. One that did know the Court,</l>
                  <l>Yet underſtood it better by report</l>
                  <l>Then practice, for he nothing took from thence</l>
                  <l>But the kings favour for his recompence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>One for religion, or his countreys good</l>
                  <l>That valu'd not his Fortune nor his blood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98172:30"/>One high in fair opinion, rich in praiſe;</l>
                  <l>And full of all we could have wiſht, but dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that is warn'd of this, and ſhall forbear</l>
                  <l>To vent a ſigh for him, or lend a tear;</l>
                  <l>May he live long and ſcorn'd, unpiti'd fall,</l>
                  <l>And want a mourner at his funerall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Extquy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ACcept thou Shrine of my dead Saint,</l>
                  <l>Inſteed of Dirges this complaint;</l>
                  <l>And for ſweet flowres to crown thy hearſe,</l>
                  <l>Receive a ſtrew of weeping verſe</l>
                  <l>From thy griev'd friend, whom thou might'ſt ſee</l>
                  <l>Quite melted into tears for thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dear loſs! ſince thy untimely fate</l>
                  <l>My task hath been to meditate</l>
                  <l>On thee, on thee: thou art the book,</l>
                  <l>The library whereon I look</l>
                  <l>Though almoſt blind. For thee (lov'd clay)</l>
                  <l>I languiſh out not live the day,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98172:30"/>Uſing no other exerciſe</l>
                  <l>But what I practiſe with mine eyes:</l>
                  <l>By which wet glaſſes I find out</l>
                  <l>How lazily time creeps about</l>
                  <l>To one that mourns: this, onely this</l>
                  <l>My exerciſe and bus'neſs is:</l>
                  <l>So I compute the weary houres</l>
                  <l>With ſighs diſſolved into ſhowres.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor wonder if my time go thus</l>
                  <l>Backward and moſt prepoſterous;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt benighted me, thy ſet</l>
                  <l>This Eve of blackneſs did beget,</l>
                  <l>Who was't my day, (though overcaſt</l>
                  <l>Before thou had'ſt thy Noon-tide paſt)</l>
                  <l>And I remember muſt in tears,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſcarce had'ſt ſeen ſo many years</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Day tells houres. By thy cleer Sun</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y love and fortune firſt did run;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut thou wilt never more appear</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olded within my Hemiſphear,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince both thy light and motion</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ike a fled Star is fall'n and gon,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98172:31"/>And twixt me and my ſoules dear wiſh</l>
                  <l>The earth now interpoſed is,</l>
                  <l>Which ſuch a ſtrange eclipſe doth make</l>
                  <l>As ne're was read in Almanake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I could allow thee for a time</l>
                  <l>To darken me and my ſad Clime,</l>
                  <l>Were it a month, a year, or ten,</l>
                  <l>I would thy exile live till then;</l>
                  <l>And all that ſpace my mirth adjourn,</l>
                  <l>So thou wouldſt promiſe to return;</l>
                  <l>And putting off thy aſhy ſhrowd</l>
                  <l>At length diſperſe this ſorrows cloud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But woe is me! the longeſt date</l>
                  <l>Too narrow is to calculate</l>
                  <l>Theſe empty hopes: never ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Be ſo much bleſt as to deſcry</l>
                  <l>A glimpſe of thee, till that day come</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall the earth to cinders doome,</l>
                  <l>And a fierce Feaver muſt calcine</l>
                  <l>The body of this world like thine,</l>
                  <l>(My Little World!) that fit of fire</l>
                  <l>Once off, our bodies ſhall aſpire</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98172:31"/>To our ſoules bliſs: then we ſhall riſe,</l>
                  <l>And view our ſelves with cleerer eyes</l>
                  <l>In that calm Region, where no night</l>
                  <l>Can hide us from each others ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mean time, thou haſt her earth: much good</l>
                  <l>May my harm do thee. Since it ſtood</l>
                  <l>With Heavens will I might not call</l>
                  <l>Her longer mine, I give thee all</l>
                  <l>My ſhort-liv'd right and intereſt</l>
                  <l>In her, whom living I lov'd beſt:</l>
                  <l>With a moſt free and bounteous grief,</l>
                  <l>I give thee what I could not keep.</l>
                  <l>Be kind to her, and prethee look</l>
                  <l>Thou write into thy Doomſ-day book</l>
                  <l>Each parcell of this Rarity</l>
                  <l>Which in thy Casket ſhrin'd doth ly:</l>
                  <l>See that thou make thy reck'ning ſtreight,</l>
                  <l>And yield her back again by weight;</l>
                  <l>For thou muſt audit on thy truſt</l>
                  <l>Each graine and atome of this duſt,</l>
                  <l>As thou wilt anſwer <hi>Him</hi> that lent,</l>
                  <l>Not gave thee my dear Monument.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98172:32"/>
                  <l>So cloſe the ground, and 'bout her ſhade</l>
                  <l>Black curtains draw, my <hi>Bride</hi> is laid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sleep on my <hi>Love</hi> in thy cold bed</l>
                  <l>Never to be diſquieted!</l>
                  <l>My laſt good night! Thou wilt not wak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till I thy fate ſhall overtake:</l>
                  <l>Till age, or grief, or ſickneſs muſt</l>
                  <l>Marry my body to that duſt</l>
                  <l>It ſo much loves; and fill the room</l>
                  <l>My heart keeps empty in thy Tomb.</l>
                  <l>Stay for me there; I will not faile</l>
                  <l>To meet thee in that hallow Vale.</l>
                  <l>And think not much of my delay;</l>
                  <l>I am already on the way,</l>
                  <l>And follow thee with all the ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Deſire can make, or ſorrows breed.</l>
                  <l>Each minute is a ſhort degree,</l>
                  <l>And ev'ry houre a ſtep towards thee.</l>
                  <l>At night when I betake to reſt,</l>
                  <l>Next morn I riſe neerer my Weſt</l>
                  <l>Of life, almoſt by eight houres ſaile,</l>
                  <l>Then when ſleep breath'd his drowſie gale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98172:32"/>
                  <l>Thus from the Sun my Bottom ſtears,</l>
                  <l>And my dayes Compaſs downward bears:</l>
                  <l>Nor labour I to ſtemme the tide</l>
                  <l>Through which to <hi>Thee</hi> I ſwiftly glide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis true, with ſhame and grief I yield,</l>
                  <l>Thou like the <hi>Vann</hi> firſt took'ſt the field,</l>
                  <l>And gotten haſt the victory</l>
                  <l>In thus adventuring to dy</l>
                  <l>Before me, whoſe more years might crave</l>
                  <l>A juſt precedence in the grave.</l>
                  <l>But heark! My Pulſe like a ſoft Drum</l>
                  <l>Beats my approch, tells <hi>Thee</hi> I come;</l>
                  <l>And ſlow howere my marches be,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall at laſt ſit down by <hi>Thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The thought of this bids me go on,</l>
                  <l>And wait my diſſolution</l>
                  <l>With hope and comfort. <hi>Dear</hi> (forgive</l>
                  <l>The crime) I am content to live</l>
                  <l>Divided, with but half a heart,</l>
                  <l>Till we ſhall meet and never part.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98172:33"/>
               <head>The Anniverſe. AN ELEGY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO ſoon grown old! haſt thou been ſix years dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Poor earth, once by my Love inhabited!</l>
                  <l>And muſt I live to calculate the time</l>
                  <l>To which thy blooming youth could never climbe,</l>
                  <l>But fell in the aſcent! yet have not I</l>
                  <l>Studi'd enough thy loſſes hiſtory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How happy were mankind if Death's ſtrict lawes</l>
                  <l>Conſum'd our lamentations like the cauſe!</l>
                  <l>Or that our grief turning to duſt might end</l>
                  <l>With the diſſolved body of a friend!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſacred Heaven! O how juſt thou art</l>
                  <l>In ſtamping deaths impreſſion on that heart</l>
                  <l>Which through thy favours would grow inſolent,</l>
                  <l>Were it not phyſick't by ſharp diſcontent.</l>
                  <l>If then it ſtand reſolv'd in thy decree</l>
                  <l>That ſtill I muſt doom'd to a Deſart be</l>
                  <l>Sprung out of my lone thoughts, which know no path</l>
                  <l>But what my own misfortune beaten hath:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:98172:33"/>If thou wilt bind me living to a coarſe,</l>
                  <l>And I muſt ſlowly waſte; I then of force</l>
                  <l>Stoop to thy great appointment, and obey</l>
                  <l>That will which nought avail me to gainſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For whil'ſt in ſorrowes Maze I wander on,</l>
                  <l>I do but follow lifes vocation.</l>
                  <l>Sure we were made to grieve: at our firſt birth</l>
                  <l>With cries we took poſſeſſion of the earth;</l>
                  <l>And though the lucky man reputed be</l>
                  <l>Fortunes adopted ſon, yet onely he</l>
                  <l>Is Natures true born child, who ſummes his years</l>
                  <l>(Like me) with no Arithmetick but tears.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:98172:34"/>
               <head>On two Children dying of one Diſeaſe, and buried in one Grave.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BRought forth in ſorrow, and bred up in care,</l>
                  <l>Two tender Children here entombed are:</l>
                  <l>One Place, one Sire, one Womb their being gave,</l>
                  <l>They had one mortal ſickneſs, and one grave.</l>
                  <l>And though they cannot number many years</l>
                  <l>In their Account, yet with their Parents tears</l>
                  <l>This comfort mingles; Though their dayes were few</l>
                  <l>They ſcarcely ſinne, but never ſorrow knew:</l>
                  <l>So that they well might boaſt, they carry'd hence</l>
                  <l>What riper ages loſe, their innocence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You pretty loſſes, that revive the fate</l>
                  <l>Which in your mother death did antedate,</l>
                  <l>O let my high-ſwol'n grief diſtill on you</l>
                  <l>The ſaddeſt drops of a Parentall dew:</l>
                  <l>You ask no other dower then what my eyes</l>
                  <l>Lay out on your untimely exequies:</l>
                  <l>When once I have diſcharg'd that mournfull skore,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n hath decreed you ne're ſhall coſt me more,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98172:34"/>Since you releaſe and quit my borrow'd truſt,</l>
                  <l>By taking this inheritance of duſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A Letter.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Ne'r was dreſt in Forms; nor can I bend</l>
                  <l>My pen to flatter any, nor commend,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs deſert or honour do preſent</l>
                  <l>Unto my verſe a worthy argument.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You are my friend, and in that word to me</l>
                  <l>Stand blazon'd in your nobleſt Heraldry;</l>
                  <l>That ſtyle preſents you full, and does relate</l>
                  <l>The bounty of your love, and my own fate,</l>
                  <l>Both which conſpir'd to make me yours. A choice</l>
                  <l>Which needs muſt in the giddy peoples voice,</l>
                  <l>That onely judge the outſide, and like apes</l>
                  <l>Play with our names, and comment on our ſhapes,</l>
                  <l>Appear too light: but it lies you upon</l>
                  <l>To juſtifie the diſproportion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Truth be my record, I durſt not preſume</l>
                  <l>To ſeek to you, 'twas you that did aſſume</l>
                  <l>Me to your boſom. Wherein you ſubdu'd</l>
                  <l>One that can ſerve you, though ne're could intrude</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98172:35"/>Upon great titles; nor knows how t'invade</l>
                  <l>Acquaintance: Like ſuch as are onely paid</l>
                  <l>With great mens ſmiles; if that the paſſant Lord</l>
                  <l>Let fall a forc't ſalute, or but afford</l>
                  <l>The Nod Regardant. It was teſt enough</l>
                  <l>For me, you ne're did find ſuch ſervile ſtuff</l>
                  <l>Couch't in my temper; I can freely ſay,</l>
                  <l>I do not love you in that common way</l>
                  <l>For which Great Ones are lov'd in this falſe time:</l>
                  <l>I have no wiſh to gain, nor will to climbe;</l>
                  <l>I cannot pawn my freedom, nor out-live</l>
                  <l>My liberty for all that you can give.</l>
                  <l>And ſure you may retain good cheap ſuch friends,</l>
                  <l>Who not your fortune make, but you, their ends.</l>
                  <l>I ſpeak not this to vaunt in my own ſtory,</l>
                  <l>All theſe additions are unto your glory;</l>
                  <l>Who counter to the world, uſe to elect,</l>
                  <l>Not to take up on truſt what you affect.</l>
                  <l>Indeed 'tis ſeldom ſeen that ſuch as you</l>
                  <l>Adopt a friend, or for acquaintance ſue;</l>
                  <l>Yet you did this vouchſafe, you did deſcend</l>
                  <l>Below your ſelf to raiſe an humble friend,</l>
                  <l>And fix him in your love: where I will ſtand</l>
                  <l>The conſtant ſubject of your free command.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98172:35"/>Had I no ayerie thoughts ſure you would teach</l>
                  <l>Me higher then my own dull ſphere to reach:</l>
                  <l>And by reflex inſtruct me to appear</l>
                  <l>Something (though courſe and plain) fit for your wear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Know, beſt of friends, however wild report</l>
                  <l>May juſtly ſay I am unapt to ſort</l>
                  <l>With your opinion or ſociety,</l>
                  <l>(Which truth would ſhame me did I it deny)</l>
                  <l>There's ſomething in me ſayes, I dare make good,</l>
                  <l>When honour calls me, all I want in blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Put off your Giant titles, then I can</l>
                  <l>Stand in your judgements blank an equal man.</l>
                  <l>Though Hills advanced are above the Plain,</l>
                  <l>They are but higher earth, nor muſt diſdain</l>
                  <l>Alliance with the Vale: we ſee a ſpade</l>
                  <l>Can level them, and make a Mount a Glade.</l>
                  <l>Howere we differ in the Heralds book,</l>
                  <l>He that mankindes extraction ſhall look</l>
                  <l>In Natures Rolles, muſt grant we all agree.</l>
                  <l>In our beſt parts, immortal pedigree:</l>
                  <l>You muſt by that perſpective onely view</l>
                  <l>My ſervice, elſe 'twill nere ſhew worthy you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:98172:36"/>
                  <l>You ſee I court you bluntly like a friend</l>
                  <l>Not like a Miſtreſs; my Muſe is not penn'd</l>
                  <l>For ſmooth and oylie flights: And I indent</l>
                  <l>To uſe more honeſty then complement.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I have done; in lieu of all you give</l>
                  <l>Receive his thankful tribute who muſt live</l>
                  <l>Your vow'd obſerver, and devotes a heart</l>
                  <l>Which will in death ſeal the bold counterpart.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>An Acknowledgment.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY beſt of friends! what needs a chain to tie</l>
                  <l>One by your merit bound a Votarie?</l>
                  <l>Think you I have ſome plot upon my peace,</l>
                  <l>I would this bondage change for a releaſe?</l>
                  <l>Since 'twas my fate your priſoner to be,</l>
                  <l>Heav'n knows I nothing fear but libertie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet you do well that ſtudy to prevent,</l>
                  <l>After ſo rich a ſtock of favour ſpent</l>
                  <l>On one ſo worthleſs, leſt my memory</l>
                  <l>Should let ſo dear an obligation dy</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:98172:36"/>Without Record. This made my precious Friend</l>
                  <l>Her Token, as an Antidote to ſend</l>
                  <l>Againſt forgetful poyſons. That as they</l>
                  <l>Who Veſpers late, and early Mattins ſay</l>
                  <l>Upon their Beads, ſo on this linked skore</l>
                  <l>In golden numbers I might reckon ore</l>
                  <l>Your vertues and my debt, which does ſurmount</l>
                  <l>The trivial laws of Popular account:</l>
                  <l>For that within this emblematick knot</l>
                  <l>Your beauteous mind, and my own fate is wrote.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſparkling conſtellation which combines</l>
                  <l>The Lock, is your dear ſelf, whoſe worth out ſhines</l>
                  <l>Moſt of your ſex: ſo ſolid and ſo clear</l>
                  <l>You like a perfect Diamond appear;</l>
                  <l>Caſting from your example fuller light</l>
                  <l>Then thoſe dimme ſparks which glaze the brow of night,</l>
                  <l>And gladding all your friends, as doth the ray</l>
                  <l>Of that Eaſt-ſtarre which wakes the cheerful day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But the black Map of death and diſcontent</l>
                  <l>Behind that Adamantine firmament,</l>
                  <l>That luckleſs figure which like Calvary</l>
                  <l>Stands ſtrew'd and coppy'd out in skuls, is I:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98172:37"/>Whoſe life your abſence clouds, and makes my time</l>
                  <l>Move blindfold in the dark ecliptick line.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then wonder not if my removed Sun</l>
                  <l>So low within the Weſtern Tropick run;</l>
                  <l>My eyes no day in this Horizon ſee,</l>
                  <l>Since where You are not all is night to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Laſtly, the anchor which enfaſtned lies</l>
                  <l>Upon a pair of deaths, ſadly applies</l>
                  <l>That Monument of Reſt which harbour muſt</l>
                  <l>Our Ship-wrackt fortunes in a road of duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So then how late ſoere my joyleſs life</l>
                  <l>Be tired out in this affections ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>Though my tempeſtuous fancie like the skie</l>
                  <l>Travail with ſtormes, and through my watry eie</l>
                  <l>Sorrows high-going waves ſpring many a leak;</l>
                  <l>Though ſighs blow loud til my hearts cordagebrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though Bath, and all my wiſhes prove untrue,</l>
                  <l>Yet Death ſhall fix and anchor Me with You.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſome poor comfort that this mortal ſcope</l>
                  <l>Will Period, though never Crown my Hope.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98172:37"/>
               <head>The Acquittance.</head>
               <l>NOt knowing who ſhould my Acquittance take,</l>
               <l>I know as little what diſcharge to make.</l>
               <l>The favour is ſo great, that it out-goes</l>
               <l>All forms of thankfulneſs I can propoſe.</l>
               <l>Thoſe grateful livies which my pen would raiſe,</l>
               <l>Are ſtricken dumb, or bury'd in amaze.</l>
               <l>Therefore, as once in Athens there was ſhown</l>
               <l>An Altar built unto the God unknown,</l>
               <l>My ignorant devotions muſt by gueſs</l>
               <l>This blind return of gratitude addreſs,</l>
               <l>Till You vouchſafe to ſhew me where and how</l>
               <l>I may to this revealed Goddeſs bow.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:98172:38"/>
               <head>The Forfeiture.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY Deareſt, To let you or the world know</l>
                  <l>What Debt of ſervice I do truly ow</l>
                  <l>To your unpattern'd ſelf, were to require</l>
                  <l>A language onely form'd in the deſire</l>
                  <l>Of him that writes. It is the common fate,</l>
                  <l>Of greateſt duties to evaporate</l>
                  <l>In ſilent meaning, as we often ſee</l>
                  <l>Fires by their too much fuel ſmother'd be:</l>
                  <l>Small Obligations may find vent and ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>When greater the unable debtor break.</l>
                  <l>And ſuch are mine to you, whoſe favours ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Hath made me poorer then I was before;</l>
                  <l>For I want words and language to declare</l>
                  <l>How ſtrict my Bond or large your bounties are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since nothing in my deſp'rate fortune found,</l>
                  <l>Can payment make, nor yet the ſumme compoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>You muſt loſe all, or elſe of force accept</l>
                  <l>The body of a Bankrupt for your debt.</l>
                  <l>Then Love, your Bond to Execution ſue,</l>
                  <l>And take my ſelf, as forfeited to you.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:98172:38"/>
               <head>The Departure. AN ELEGY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVEre I to leave no more then a good friend,</l>
                  <l>Or but to hear the ſummons to my end,</l>
                  <l>(Which I have long'd for) I could then with eaſe</l>
                  <l>Attire my grief in words, and ſo appeaſe</l>
                  <l>That paſſion in my boſom, which outgrowes</l>
                  <l>The language of ſtrict verſe or largeſt proſe.</l>
                  <l>But here I am quite loſt; writing to you</l>
                  <l>All that I pen or think, is forc't and new.</l>
                  <l>My faculties run croſs, and prove as weak</l>
                  <l>T'indite this melancholly task, as ſpeak:</l>
                  <l>Indeed all words are vain, well might I ſpare</l>
                  <l>This rendring of my tortur'd thoughts in ayre,</l>
                  <l>Or ſighing paper. My infectious grief</l>
                  <l>Strikes inward, and affords me no relief.</l>
                  <l>But ſtill a deeper wound, to loſe a ſight</l>
                  <l>More lov'd then health, and dearer then the light.</l>
                  <l>But all of us were not at the ſame time</l>
                  <l>Brought forth, nor are we billited in one clime.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:98172:39"/>Nature hath pitch't mankind at ſeveral rates,</l>
                  <l>Making our places diverſe as our fates.</l>
                  <l>Unto that univerſal law I bow,</l>
                  <l>Though with unwilling knee; and do allow</l>
                  <l>Her cruell juſtice, which diſpos'd us ſo</l>
                  <l>That we muſt counter to our wiſhes go.</l>
                  <l>'Twas part of mans firſt curſe, which order'd well</l>
                  <l>We ſhould not alway with our likings dwell.</l>
                  <l>'Tis onely the Triumphant Church where we</l>
                  <l>Shall in unſever'd Neighbourhood agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go then beſt ſoul, and where You muſt appear</l>
                  <l>Reſtore the Day to that dull Hemiſphear.</l>
                  <l>Nere may the hapleſs Night You leave behind</l>
                  <l>Darken the comforts of Your purer mind.</l>
                  <l>May all the bleſſings Wiſhes can invent</l>
                  <l>Enrich your dayes, and crown them with content.</l>
                  <l>And though You travel down into the Weſt,</l>
                  <l>May Your lifes Sun ſtand fixed in the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>Far from the weeping ſet; nor may my car</l>
                  <l>Take in that killing whiſper, <hi>You once were.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus kiſs I your fair hands, taking my leave</l>
                  <l>As Priſoners at the Bar their doom receive,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:98172:39"/>All joyes go with You: let ſweet peace attend</l>
                  <l>You on the way, and wait Your journeys end.</l>
                  <l>But let Your diſcontents, and ſowrer fate</l>
                  <l>Remain with me, born off in my Retrait.</l>
                  <l>Might all your croſſes in that ſheet of lead</l>
                  <l>Which folds my heavy heart lie buried:</l>
                  <l>'Tis the laſt ſervice I would do You, and the beſt</l>
                  <l>My wiſhes ever meant, or tongue profeſt.</l>
                  <l>Once more I take my leave. And once for all,</l>
                  <l>Our parting ſhews ſo like a funerall,</l>
                  <l>It ſtrikes my ſoul, which hath moſt right to be</l>
                  <l>Chief Mourner at this ſad ſolemnitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And think not, Deareſt, 'cauſe this parting knell</l>
                  <l>Is rung in verſes, that at Your farewell</l>
                  <l>I onely mourn in Poetry and Ink:</l>
                  <l>No, my Pens melancholy Plommets ſink</l>
                  <l>So low, they dive where th' hid affections ſit,</l>
                  <l>Blotting that Paper where my mirth was writ.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Believ't that ſorrow trueſt is which lies</l>
                  <l>Deep in the breaſt, not floating in the eies:</l>
                  <l>And he with ſaddeſt circumſtance doth part,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeals his farewell with a bleeding heart,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:98172:40"/>
               <head>PARADOX. That it is beſt for a Young Maid to marry an Old Man.</head>
               <l>FAir one, why cannot you an old man love?</l>
               <l>He may as uſeful, and more conſtant prove.</l>
               <l>Experience ſhews you that maturer years</l>
               <l>Are a ſecurity againſt thoſe fears</l>
               <l>Youth will expoſe you to; whoſe wild deſire</l>
               <l>As it is hot, ſo 'tis as raſh as fire.</l>
               <l>Mark how the blaze extinct in a ſhes lies,</l>
               <l>Leaving no brand nor embers when it dies</l>
               <l>Which might the flame renew: thus ſoon conſumes</l>
               <l>Youths wandring hear, and vaniſhes in fumes.</l>
               <l>When ages riper love unapt to ſtray</l>
               <l>Through looſe and giddy change of objects, may</l>
               <l>In your warm boſom like a cynder lie,</l>
               <l>Quickned and kindled by your ſparkling eie.</l>
               <l>'Tis not deni'd, there are extremes in both</l>
               <l>Which may the fancie move to like or loath:</l>
               <l>Yet of the two you better ſhall endure</l>
               <l>To marry with the Cramp then Calenture.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98172:40"/>Who would in wiſdom chooſe the Torrid Zone</l>
               <l>Therein to ſettle a Plantation?</l>
               <l>Merchants can tell you, thoſe hot Climes were made</l>
               <l>But at the longeſt for a three years trade:</l>
               <l>And though the Indies caſt the ſweeter ſmell,</l>
               <l>Yet health and plenty do more Northward dwell';</l>
               <l>For where the raging Sun-beams burn the earth,</l>
               <l>Her ſcorched mantle withers into dearth;</l>
               <l>Yet when that drought becomes the Harveſts curſe,</l>
               <l>Snow doth the tender Corn moſt kindly nurſe:</l>
               <l>Why now then wooe you not ſome ſnowy head</l>
               <l>To take you in meer pitty to his bed?</l>
               <l>I doubt the harder task were to perſwade</l>
               <l>Him to love you: for if what I have ſaid</l>
               <l>In Virgins as in Vegetals holds true,</l>
               <l>Hee'l prove the better Nurſe to cheriſh you.</l>
               <l>Some men we know renown'd for wiſdom grown</l>
               <l>By old records and antique Medalls ſhown;</l>
               <l>Why ought not women then be held moſt wiſe</l>
               <l>Who can produce living antiquities?</l>
               <l>Beſides if care of that main happineſs</l>
               <l>Your ſex triumphs in, doth your thoughts poſſeſs,</l>
               <l>I mean your beauty from decay to keep;</l>
               <l>No waſh nor mask is like an old mans ſleep.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:98172:41"/>Young wives need never to be Sun-burnt fear,</l>
               <l>Who their old husbands for Umbrellaes wear:</l>
               <l>How ruſſet looks an Orchard on the hill</l>
               <l>To one that's water'd by ſome neighh'ring Drill?</l>
               <l>Are not the floated Medowes ever ſeen</l>
               <l>To flouriſh ſooneſt, and hold longeſt green?</l>
               <l>You may be ſure no moiſt'ning lacks that Bride,</l>
               <l>Who lies with Winter thawing by her ſide.</l>
               <l>She-ſhould be fruitful too as fields that joyne</l>
               <l>Unto the melting waſte of <hi>Appenine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whil'ſt the cold morning-drops bedew the Roſe,</l>
               <l>It doth nor leaf, nor ſmell, nor colour loſe;</l>
               <l>Then doubt not Sweet! Age hath ſupplies of wet</l>
               <l>To keep You like that flowr in water ſet.</l>
               <l>Dripping Catarrhs and Fontinells are things</l>
               <l>Will make You think You grew betwixt two Springs.</l>
               <l>And ſhould You not think ſo, You ſcarce allow</l>
               <l>The force or Merit of Your Marriage-Vow;</l>
               <l>Where maids a new Creed learn, &amp; muſt from thence</l>
               <l>Believe againſt their own or others ſence.</l>
               <l>Elſe Love will nothing differ from neglect,</l>
               <l>Which turns not to a vertue each defect.</l>
               <l>Ile ſay no more but this; you women make</l>
               <l>Your Childrens reck'ning by the Almanake.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:98172:41"/>I like it well, ſo you contented are,</l>
               <l>To chooſe their Fethers by that Kalendar.</l>
               <l>Turn then old <hi>Erra Pater,</hi> and there ſee</l>
               <l>According to lifes poſture and degree,</l>
               <l>What age or what complexion is moſt fit</l>
               <l>To make an Engliſh Maid happy by it;</l>
               <l>And You ſhall find, if You will chooſe a man,</l>
               <l>Set juſtly for Your own Meridian,</l>
               <l>Though You perhaps let <hi>One</hi> and <hi>Twenty</hi> woo,</l>
               <l>Your elevation is for <hi>Fifty Two.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>PARADOX. That Fruition deſtroyes Love.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LOve is our Reaſons Paradox, which ſtill</l>
                  <l>A gainſt the judgment doth maintain the Will:</l>
                  <l>And governs by ſuch arbitrary laws,</l>
                  <l>It onely makes the Act our Likings cauſe:</l>
                  <l>We have no brave revenge, but to forgo</l>
                  <l>Our full deſires, and ſtarve the Tyrant ſo.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They whom the riſing blood tempts not to taſte,</l>
                  <l>Preſerve a ſtock of Love can never waſte;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:98172:42"/>When eaſie people who their wiſh enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Like Prodigalls at once their wealth deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> till now had ſtayd in Paradiſe</l>
                  <l>Had his deſires been bounded by his eyes.</l>
                  <l>When he did more then look, that made th'offence,</l>
                  <l>And forfeited his ſtate of innocence.</l>
                  <l>Fruition therefore is the bane t'undoe</l>
                  <l>Both our affection and the ſubject too.</l>
                  <l>'Tis Love into worſe language to tranſlate,</l>
                  <l>And make it into Luſt degenerate:</l>
                  <l>'Tis to De-throne, and thruſt it from the heart,</l>
                  <l>To ſeat it groſſely in the ſenſual part.</l>
                  <l>Seek for the <hi>Starre</hi> that's <hi>ſhot</hi> upon the ground,</l>
                  <l>And nought but a dimme gelly there is found.</l>
                  <l>Thus foul and dark our female ſtarre sappear,</l>
                  <l>If fall'n or looſned once from Vertues Sphear.</l>
                  <l>Glow-worms ſhine onely look't on, and let ly,</l>
                  <l>But handled crawl into deformity:</l>
                  <l>So beauty is no longer fair and bright,</l>
                  <l>Then whil'ſt unſtained by the appetite:</l>
                  <l>And then it withers like a blaſted flowre</l>
                  <l>Some poys'nous worm or ſpider hath creptiore.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pigmaleon</hi>'s dotage on the carved ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Shews Amoriſts their ſtrong illuſion.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:98172:42"/>Whil'ſt he to gaze and court it was content,</l>
                  <l>He ſerv'd as Prieſt at beauties Monument:</l>
                  <l>But when by looſer fires t'embraces led,</l>
                  <l>It prov'd a cold hard Statue in his bed.</l>
                  <l>Irregular affects, like mad mens dreams</l>
                  <l>Preſented by falſe lights and broken beams,</l>
                  <l>So long content us, as no neer addreſs</l>
                  <l>Shews the weak ſenſe our painted happineſs.</l>
                  <l>But when thoſe pleaſing ſhaddowes us forſake,</l>
                  <l>Or of the ſubſtance we a trial make,</l>
                  <l>Like him, deluded by the fancies mock,</l>
                  <l>We ſhip-wrack 'gainſt an Alabaſter rock.</l>
                  <l>What though thy Miſtreſs far from Marble be?</l>
                  <l>Her ſoftneſs will transform and harden thee.</l>
                  <l>Luſt is a Snake, and Guilt the Gorgons head,</l>
                  <l>Which Conſcience turns to Stone, &amp; Joyes to Lead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turtles themſelves will bluſh, if put to name</l>
                  <l>The Act, whereby they quench their am'rous flame.</l>
                  <l>Who then that's wiſe or vertuous, would not feare</l>
                  <l>To catch at pleaſures which forbidden were,</l>
                  <l>When thoſe which we count lawful, cannot be</l>
                  <l>Requir'd without ſome loſs of modeſtie?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:98172:43"/>Ev'n in the Marriage-Bed, where ſoft delights.</l>
                  <l>Are cuſtomary and authoriz'd Rites;</l>
                  <l>What are thoſe tributes to the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> fenſe,</l>
                  <l>But toleration of Incontinence?</l>
                  <l>For properly you cannot call that Love</l>
                  <l>Which does not from the Soul, but Humour move.</l>
                  <l>Thus they who worſhipt <hi>Pun</hi> or <hi>1ſt</hi> Shrine,</l>
                  <l>By the fair Front judg'd all within Divine:</l>
                  <l>Though entring, found 'twas but a Goat or Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>To which before their ignorance did b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Such Temples and ſuch God deſſes are theſe</l>
                  <l>Which fooliſh Lovers and admirers pleaſe:</l>
                  <l>Who if they chance within the Shrine to prie,</l>
                  <l>Find that a beaſt they thought a Deity.</l>
                  <l>Nor makes it onely our opinion leſs</l>
                  <l>Of what we lik't before, and now poſſeſs;</l>
                  <l>But robbs the Fuel, and corrupts the Spice</l>
                  <l>Which ſweetens and inflames Loves ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>After Fruition once, what is Deſire</l>
                  <l>But aſhes kept warm by a dying fire?</l>
                  <l>This is (if any) the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which ſtill miſcarries at <hi>Projection.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For when the <hi>Heat ad Octo</hi> intermits,</l>
                  <l>It poorly takes us like Third Ague fits;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:98172:43"/>Or muſt on Embers as dull Druggs infuſe,</l>
                  <l>Which we for Med'cine not for Pleaſure uſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since Lovers joyes then leave ſo ſick a taſte,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon as reliſh'd by the Senſe are paſt;</l>
                  <l>They are but Riddies ſure, loſt if poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>And therefore onely in Reverſion beſt.</l>
                  <l>For bate them Expectation and Delay,</l>
                  <l>You take the moſt delightful Scenes away.</l>
                  <l>Theſe two ſuch rule within the fancie keep,</l>
                  <l>As banquets apprehended in our ſleep;</l>
                  <l>After which pleaſing trance next morn we wake</l>
                  <l>Empty and angry at the nights miſtake.</l>
                  <l>Give me long Dreams and Viſions of content,</l>
                  <l>Rather then pleaſures in a minute ſpent.</l>
                  <l>And ſince I know before, the ſhedding Roſe</l>
                  <l>In that ſame inſtant doth her ſweetneſs loſe,</l>
                  <l>Upon the Virgin-ſtock ſtill let her dwell</l>
                  <l>For me, to feaſt my longings with her ſmell.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe are but counterfeits of joy at beſt,</l>
                  <l>Which languiſh ſoon as brought unto the teſt.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I hold it worth his pains who tries</l>
                  <l>To Inne that Harveſt which by reaping dies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:98172:44"/>
                  <l>Reſolve me now what ſpirit hath delight,</l>
                  <l>It by full feed you kill the appetite?</l>
                  <l>That ſtomack healthy'ſt is, that nere was cloy'd,</l>
                  <l>Why not that Love the beſt then, nere enjoy'd?</l>
                  <l>Since nat'rally the blood, when tam'd or ſated,</l>
                  <l>Will cool ſo faſt it leaves the object hated.</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures like wonders quickly loſe their price</l>
                  <l>When Reaſon or Experience makes us wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To cloſe my argument then. I dare ſay</l>
                  <l>(And without Paradox) as well we may</l>
                  <l>Enjoy our Love and yet preſerve Deſire,</l>
                  <l>As warm our hands by putting out the fire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:98172:44"/>
               <head>The Change Il ſabio mude conſeio: Il loco perſevera.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WE lov'd as friends now twenty years and more:</l>
                  <l>Is't time or reaſon think you to give o're?</l>
                  <l>When though two prentiſhips ſet Jacob free,</l>
                  <l>I have not held my Rachel dear at three.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet will I not your levitle accuſe;</l>
                  <l>Continuance ſometimes is the worſe abuſe.</l>
                  <l>In judgment I might rather hold it ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>If like the fleeting world, you did not change:</l>
                  <l>Be it your wiſdom therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to retract,</l>
                  <l>When perſeverance oft is follies act.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In pity I can think, that what you do</l>
                  <l>Hath Juſtice in't, and ſome Religion too;</l>
                  <l>For of all vertues Morall or Divine,</l>
                  <l>We know but Love none muſt in Heaven ſhine:</l>
                  <l>Well did you the preſumption then foreſee</l>
                  <l>Of counterfeiting immortalitie:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:98172:45"/>Since had you kept our loves too long alive,</l>
                  <l>We might invade Heavens prerogative;</l>
                  <l>Or in our progreſs, like the Jews, compriſe</l>
                  <l>The Legend of an earthly Paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Live happy and more proſperous in the next,</l>
                  <l>You have diſcharg'd your old friend by the Text.</l>
                  <l>Farewel fair Shadow of a female faith,</l>
                  <l>And let this be our friendſhips Epitaph:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Affection ſhares the frailty of our fate,</l>
                  <l>When (like our ſelves) 'tis old and out of date:</l>
                  <l>'Tis juſt all humane Loves their period have,</l>
                  <l>When friends are frail and dropping to the gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:98172:45"/>
               <head>To my Sister Anne King, who chid me in verſe for being angry.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>DEar Nan, I would not have thy counſel loſt,</l>
                  <l>Though I laſt night had twice ſo much been croſt;</l>
                  <l>Well is a Paſſion to the Market brought,</l>
                  <l>When ſuch a treaſure of advice is bought</l>
                  <l>With ſo much droſs. And could'ſt thou me aſſure,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ach vice of mine ſhould meet with ſuch a cure,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> would ſin oft, and on my guilty brow</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear every miſperfection that I ow,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pen and viſible; I ſhould not hide</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut bring my faults abroad: to hear thee chide</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch a Note, and with a Quill ſo ſage,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Paſſion tunes, and calmes a Tempeſts rage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Well I am charm'd, and promiſe to redreſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat, without ſhrift, my follies doe confeſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainſt my ſelf: wherefore let me intreat,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen I fly out in that diſtemper'd heat</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich frets me into faſts, thou wilt reprove</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat froward ſpleen in Poetry and Love:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> though I loſe my reaſon in ſuch fits,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oul't time me back again into my wits.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:98172:46"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the immature loſs of the moſt vertuous Lady Anne Rich.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Envy not thy mortal triumphs, Death,</l>
                  <l>(Thou enemy to Vertue as to Breath)</l>
                  <l>Nor do I wonder much, nor yet complain</l>
                  <l>The weekly numbers by thy arrow ſlain.</l>
                  <l>The whole world is thy Factory, and we</l>
                  <l>Like traffick driven and retail'd by Thee:</l>
                  <l>And where the ſprings of life fill up ſo faſt,</l>
                  <l>Some of the waters needs muſt run to waſte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is confeſt, yet muſt our griefs diſpute</l>
                  <l>That which thine own concluſion doth refute</l>
                  <l>Ere we begin. Hearken! for if thy ear</l>
                  <l>Be to thy throat proportion'd, thou canſt hear.</l>
                  <l>Is there no order in the work of Fate?</l>
                  <l>Nor rule, but blindly to anticipate</l>
                  <l>Our growing ſeaſons or think'ſt thou 'tis juſt,</l>
                  <l>To ſprinkle our freſh bloſſomes with thy duſt,</l>
                  <l>Till by abortive funerals, thou bring</l>
                  <l>That to an Autumn Nature meant a Spring?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:98172:46"/>Is't not enough for thee that wither'd age</l>
                  <l>Lies the unpiti'd ſubject of thy rage;</l>
                  <l>But like an ugly Amoriſt, thy creſt</l>
                  <l>Muſt be with ſpoyles of Youth and Beauty dreſt?</l>
                  <l>In other Camps, thoſe which ſate down to day</l>
                  <l>March firſt to morrow, and they longeſt ſtay</l>
                  <l>Who laſt came to the ſervice: But in thine,</l>
                  <l>Onely confuſion ſtands for diſcipline.</l>
                  <l>We fall in ſuch promiſcuous heaps, none can</l>
                  <l>Put any diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rence 'twixt thy Rear or Van;</l>
                  <l>Since oft the youngeſt lead thy Files. For this</l>
                  <l>The grieved world here thy accuſer is,</l>
                  <l>And I a Plaintiff, 'mongſt thoſe many ones</l>
                  <l>Who wet this Ladies Urn with zealous moanes;</l>
                  <l>As if her aſhes quick'ning into years</l>
                  <l>Might be again embody'd by our tears</l>
                  <l>But all in vain; the moiſture we beſtow</l>
                  <l>Shall make aſſoon her curled Marble grow,</l>
                  <l>As render heat, or motion to that blood,</l>
                  <l>Which through her veins branch't like an azurè flood;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe now ſtill Current in the grave is loſt,</l>
                  <l>Lock't up, and feeter'd by eternal froſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:98172:47"/>
                  <l>Deſiſt from hence, doting Aſtrology!</l>
                  <l>To ſearch for hidden wonders in the sky;</l>
                  <l>Or from the concourſe of malignant ſtarres</l>
                  <l>Foretel diſeaſes gen'ral as our warres:</l>
                  <l>What barren droughts, forerunners of lean dearth</l>
                  <l>Threaten to ſtarve the plenty of the earth:</l>
                  <l>What horrid forms of darkneſs muſt affright</l>
                  <l>The ſickly world, haſt'ning to that long night</l>
                  <l>Where it muſt end. If there no Portents are,</l>
                  <l>No black eclipſes for the Kalendar,</l>
                  <l>Our times ſad Annals will remembred be</l>
                  <l>Ith'loſs of bright <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Thee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two Starres of Court,</hi> who in one fatal year</l>
                  <l>By moſt untimely ſet dropt from their Sphear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shee</hi> in the winter took her flight, and ſoon</l>
                  <l>As her perfections reach't the point of Noon,</l>
                  <l>Wrapt in a cloud, contracted her wiſht ſtay</l>
                  <l>Unto the meaſure of a ſhort-liv'd day.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Thou</hi> in Summer, like an early Roſe</l>
                  <l>By Deaths cold hand nipp'd as <hi>Thou</hi> didſt diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>Took'ſt a long day to run that narrow ſtage,</l>
                  <l>Which in two gaſping minutes ſumm'd thy age.</l>
                  <l>And, as the fading Roſe, when the leaves ſhed</l>
                  <l>Lies in its native ſweetneſs buried,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:98172:47"/>
                     <hi>Thou</hi> in thy vertues bedded and inherſt</l>
                  <l>Sleep'ſt with thoſe odours thy pure fame diſperſt.</l>
                  <l>Where till that <hi>Riſing Morn</hi> thou muſt remain,</l>
                  <l>In which thy wither'd flowres ſhall ſpring again.</l>
                  <l>And greater beauties thy wak't body veſt</l>
                  <l>Then were at thy departure here poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So with full eyes we cloſe thy vault. Content</l>
                  <l>(With what thy loſs bequeaths us) to lament,</l>
                  <l>And make that uſe of thy griev'd funerall,</l>
                  <l>As of a Chryſtall broken in the fall;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pitti'd fractures gather'd up, and ſet,</l>
                  <l>May ſmaller <hi>Mirrours</hi> for <hi>Thy Sex</hi> beget;</l>
                  <l>There let them view themſelves, untill they ſee</l>
                  <l>The end of all their glories ſhew'n in <hi>Thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whil'ſt in the truth of this ſad tribute, I</l>
                  <l>Thus ſtrive to Canonize thy Memory.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:98172:48"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Mrs. Kirk unfortunately drowned in Thames.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FOr all the Ship-wracks, and the liquid graves</l>
                  <l>Loſt men have gain'd within the furrow'd waves,</l>
                  <l>The Sea hath fin'd and for our wrongs paid uſe,</l>
                  <l>When its wrought foam a <hi>Venus</hi> did produce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what repair wilt thou unhappy <hi>Thames</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Afford our loſſe? thy dull unactive ſtreames</l>
                  <l>Can no new beauty raiſe, nor yet reſtore</l>
                  <l>Her who by thee was raviſht from our ſhore:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe death hath ſtain'd the glory of thy flood,</l>
                  <l>And mixt the guilty Channel with her blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <hi>Neptune!</hi> was thy favour onely writ</l>
                  <l>In that looſe Element where thou doſt ſit?</l>
                  <l>That after all this time thou ſhould'ſt repent</l>
                  <l>Thy faireſt bleſſing to the Continent?</l>
                  <l>Say, what could urge this Fate? is <hi>Thetis</hi> dead,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Amphitrite</hi> from thy wet armes fled?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:98172:48"/>Was't thou ſo poor in Nymphs, that thy moiſt love</l>
                  <l>Muſt be maintain'd with penſions from above?</l>
                  <l>If none of theſe, but that whil'ſt thou did'ſt ſleep</l>
                  <l>Upon thy ſandy pillow in the deep,</l>
                  <l>This miſchief ſtole upon us: may our grief</l>
                  <l>Waken thy juſt revenge on that lie thief,</l>
                  <l>Who in thy fluid Empire without leave,</l>
                  <l>And unſuſpected, durſt her life bereave.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth invert thy order, and provide</l>
                  <l>In gentleſt floods a Pilot for our guide.</l>
                  <l>Let rugged Seas be lov'd, but the Brooks ſmile</l>
                  <l>Shunn'd like the courtſhip of a Crocodile;</l>
                  <l>And where the Current doth moſt ſmoothly paſs,</l>
                  <l>Think for her ſake that ſtream deaths Looking-glaſs,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew us our deſtruction is moſt neer,</l>
                  <l>When pleaſure hath begot leaſt ſenſe of fear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Elſe break thy forked Scepter 'gainſt ſome Rock,</l>
                  <l>If thou endure a flatt'ring calm to mock</l>
                  <l>Thy far-fam'd pow'r, and violate that law</l>
                  <l>Which keeps the angry Ocean in aw.</l>
                  <l>Thy Trident will grow uſeleſs, which doth ſtill</l>
                  <l>Wild tempeſts, if thou let tame rivers kill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:98172:49"/>
                  <l>Mean time we ow thee nothing. Our firſt debt</l>
                  <l>Lies cancell'd in thy wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry Cabinet.</l>
                  <l>We have for <hi>Her</hi> thou ſent'ſt us from the Main,</l>
                  <l>Return'd a <hi>Venus</hi> back to thee again.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the death of Mr. <hi>Edward Holt.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHether thy Fathers, or diſeaſes rage,</l>
                  <l>More mortal prov'd to thy unhappy age,</l>
                  <l>Our ſorrow needs not queſtion; ſince the firſt</l>
                  <l>Is known for length and ſharpneſs much the worſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy Feaver yet was kind; which the ninth day</l>
                  <l>For thy misfortunes made an eaſie way.</l>
                  <l>When th'other barbarous and Hectick fit,</l>
                  <l>In nineteen winters did not intermit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I therefore vainly now not ask thee why</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt ſo ſoon in thy Youths mid way dy:</l>
                  <l>But in my ſence the greater wonder make</l>
                  <l>Thy long oppreſſed heart no ſooner brake.</l>
                  <l>Of force m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt the neglected bloſſom all</l>
                  <l>When the tough root becomes unnaturall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:98172:49"/>And to his branches doth that ſap deny,</l>
                  <l>Which them with life and verdure ſhould ſupply.</l>
                  <l>For Parents ſhame, let it forgotten be,</l>
                  <l>And may the ſad example die with thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is not now thy grieved friends intent</l>
                  <l>To render thee dull Pities argument.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a bolder title unto fame,</l>
                  <l>And at Edge-Hill thou didſt make good the claime;</l>
                  <l>When in thy Royal Maſters Cauſe and Warre</l>
                  <l>Thy ventur'd life brought off a noble skarre.</l>
                  <l>Nor did thy faithful ſervices deſiſt</l>
                  <l>Till death untimely ſtrook thee from the Liſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though in that prouder vault then, which doth tomb</l>
                  <l>Thy anceſtors, thy body find not room,</l>
                  <l>Thine own deſerts have purchas'd thee a place,</l>
                  <l>Which more renowned is then all thy race;</l>
                  <l>For in this earth thou doſt ennobled ly</l>
                  <l>With marks of Valour and of Loyalty.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:98172:50"/>
               <head>To my dead friend Ben: Johnſon:</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I See that wreath which doth the wearer arm</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt the quick ſtrokes of thunder, is no charm</l>
                  <l>To keep off deaths pale dart. For, <hi>Johnſon</hi> then</l>
                  <l>Thou hadſt been number'd ſtill with living men.</l>
                  <l>Times ſithe had fear'd thy Lawrel to invade,</l>
                  <l>Nor thee this ſubject of our ſorrow made.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Amongſt thoſe many votaries who come</l>
                  <l>To offer up their Garlands at thy Tombe;</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt ſome more lofty pens in their bright verſe</l>
                  <l>(Like glorious Tapers flaming on thy herſe)</l>
                  <l>Shall light the dull and thankleſs world to ſee,</l>
                  <l>How great a maim it ſuffers wanting thee;</l>
                  <l>Let not thy learned ſhadow ſcorn, that I</l>
                  <l>Pay meaner Rites unto thy memory;</l>
                  <l>And ſince I nought can adde, but in deſire</l>
                  <l>Reſtore ſome ſparks which leapt from thine own fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ends ſoever others quills invite,</l>
                  <l>I can proteſt, it was no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tch to write,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98172:50"/>Nor any vain ambition to be read,</l>
                  <l>But meerly Love and Juſtice to the dead</l>
                  <l>Which rais'd my fameleſs Muſe; and caus'd her bring</l>
                  <l>Theſe drops, as tribute thrown into that ſpring,</l>
                  <l>To whoſe moſt rich and fruitful head we ow</l>
                  <l>The pureſt ſtreams of language which can flow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For 'tis but truth, thou taught'ſt the ruder age</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake by Grammar, and reform'dſt the Stage:</l>
                  <l>Thy Comick Sock induc'd ſuch purged ſence,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Lucrece</hi> might have heard without offence.</l>
                  <l>Amongſt thoſe ſoaring wits that did dilate</l>
                  <l>Our Engliſh, and advance it to the rate</l>
                  <l>And value it now holds, thy ſelf was one</l>
                  <l>Helpt lift it up to ſuch proportion.</l>
                  <l>That thus refin'd and roab'd, it ſhall not ſpare</l>
                  <l>With the full <hi>Greck</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> to compare.</l>
                  <l>For what tongue ever durſt, but ours, tranſlate</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Tully</hi>'s Eloquence, or <hi>Homers</hi> State?</l>
                  <l>Both which in their unblemiſht luſtre ſhine,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Chapmans</hi> pen, and from thy <hi>Catiline.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All I would ask for thee, in recompence</l>
                  <l>Of thy ſucceſsful toyl and times expence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98172:51"/>Is onely this poor Boon: that thoſe who can</l>
                  <l>Perhaps read <hi>French,</hi> or talk <hi>Italian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or do the lofty <hi>Spaniard</hi> affect;</l>
                  <l>To ſhew their skill in Forrein Dialect,</l>
                  <l>Prove not themſelves ſo unnaturally wife,</l>
                  <l>They therefore ſhould their <hi>Mother-tongue</hi> deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>(As if her Poets both for ſtyle and wit</l>
                  <l>Not equall'd, or not paſs'd their beſt that writ)</l>
                  <l>Untill by ſtudying <hi>Johnſon</hi> they have known</l>
                  <l>The height and ſtrength and plenty of their own.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus in what low earth or neglected room</l>
                  <l>Soere thou ſleep'ſt, <hi>thy book</hi> ſhall be thy tomb.</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt go down a happy Coarſe, beſtrew'd</l>
                  <l>With thine own Flowres; and feel thy ſelf renew'd,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt thy immortal neve-with'ring Bayes</l>
                  <l>Shall yearly flouriſh in thy Readers praiſe.</l>
                  <l>And when more ſpreading Titles are forgot,</l>
                  <l>Or ſpight of all their Lead and Sear-cloth rot,</l>
                  <l>Thou wrapt and Shrin'd in <hi>thine own ſheets,</hi> wilt ly</l>
                  <l>A Relick fam'd by all Poſterity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98172:51"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Prince Henry's death.</head>
               <l>KEep ſtation Nature, and reſt Heaven ſure</l>
               <l>On thy ſupporters ſhoulders, leſt paſt cure,</l>
               <l>Thou daſht in ruine fall by a griefs weight</l>
               <l>Will make thy baſis ſhrink, and lay thy height</l>
               <l>Low as the Center. Heark! and feel it read</l>
               <l>Through the aſtoniſht Kingdom, Henry's dead.</l>
               <l>It is enough; who ſeeks to aggravate</l>
               <l>One ſtrain beyond this, prove more ſharp his fate</l>
               <l>Then ſad our doom. The world dares not ſurvive</l>
               <l>To parallel this woes ſuperlative.</l>
               <l>O killing Rhetorick of Death! two words</l>
               <l>Breathe ſtronger terrours then Plague, Fire, or Swords</l>
               <l>Ere conquer'd. This were Epitaph and Verſe</l>
               <l>Worthy to be prefixt in Natures herſe,</l>
               <l>Or Earths ſad diſſolution; whoſe fall</l>
               <l>Will be leſs grievous though more generall:</l>
               <l>For all the woe ruine ere buried,</l>
               <l>Sounds in theſe fatal accents, Henry's dead.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:98172:52"/>Ceaſe then unable Poetry, thy phraſe</l>
               <l>Is weak and dull to ſtrike us with amaze</l>
               <l>Worthy thy vaſter ſubject. Let none dare</l>
               <l>To coppy this ſad hap, but with deſpair</l>
               <l>Hanging at his quills point. For not a ſtream</l>
               <l>Of Ink can write much leſs improve this Theam.</l>
               <l>Invention higheſt wrought by grief or wit</l>
               <l>Muſt ſink with him, and on his Tomb-ſtone ſplit.</l>
               <l>Who, like the dying Sun, tells us the light</l>
               <l>And glory of our Day ſet in his Night.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98172:52"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon S. W. R.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Will not weep, for 'twere as great a ſin</l>
                  <l>To ſhed a tear for thee, as to have bin</l>
                  <l>An Actor in thy death. Thy life and age</l>
                  <l>Was but a various Scene on fortunes Stage,</l>
                  <l>With whom thou tugg'ſt &amp; ſtrov'ſt ev'n out of breath</l>
                  <l>In thy long toil: nere maſter'd till thy death;</l>
                  <l>And then deſpight of trains and cruell wit,</l>
                  <l>Thou did'ſt at once ſubdue malice and it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I dare not then ſo blaſt thy memory</l>
                  <l>As ſay I do lament or pity thee.</l>
                  <l>Were I to chooſe a ſubject to beſtow</l>
                  <l>My pity on, he ſhould be one as low</l>
                  <l>In ſpirit as deſert. That durſt not dy</l>
                  <l>But rather were content by ſlavery</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe life: or I would pity thoſe</l>
                  <l>Thy moſt induſtrious and friendly foes:</l>
                  <l>Who when they thought to makethee ſcandals ſtory</l>
                  <l>Lent thee a ſwifter flight to Heav'n and glory.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:98172:53"/>That thought by cutting off ſome wither'd dayes,</l>
                  <l>(Which thou could'ſt ſpare them) to eclipſe thy praiſe;</l>
                  <l>Yet gave it brighter foil, made thy ag'd fame</l>
                  <l>Appear more white and fair, then foul their ſhame:</l>
                  <l>And did promote an Execution</l>
                  <l>Which (but for them) Nature and Age had done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such worthleſs things as theſe were onely born</l>
                  <l>To live on Pities almes (too mean for ſcorn.)</l>
                  <l>Thou dy'dſt an envious wonder, whoſe high fate</l>
                  <l>The world muſt ſtill admire, ſcarce imitate.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:98172:53"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the L. Biſhop of London John King.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SAd Relick of a bleſſed Soul! whoſe truſt</l>
                  <l>We ſealed up in this religious duſt.</l>
                  <l>O do not thy low Exequies ſuſpect</l>
                  <l>As the cheap arguments of our neglect.</l>
                  <l>'Twas a commanded duty that thy grave</l>
                  <l>As little pride as thou thy ſelf ſhould have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore thy covering is an humble ſtone,</l>
                  <l>And but a word<note n="*" place="margin">Reſurgam.</note> for thy inſcription.</l>
                  <l>When thoſe that in the ſame earth neighbour thee,</l>
                  <l>Have each his Chronicle and Pedigree:</l>
                  <l>They have their waving pennons and their flagges,</l>
                  <l>Of Matches and Alliance formal bragges.)</l>
                  <l>VVhen thou (although from <hi>Anceſtors</hi> thou came</l>
                  <l>Old as the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> great as thy <hi>Name</hi>)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leep'ſt there inſhrin'd in thy admired parts,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd haſt no Heraldry but thy deſerts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98172:54"/>Yet let not <hi>Them</hi> their prouder Marbles boaſt,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>They</hi> reſt with leſs honour, though more coſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go, ſearch the world, and with your Mattox woun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>The groaning boſom of the patient ground:</l>
                  <l>Digge from the hidden veins of her dark womb</l>
                  <l>All that is rare and precious for a tomb:</l>
                  <l>Yet when much treaſure, and more time is ſpent</l>
                  <l>You muſt grant <hi>His</hi> the nobler Monument.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> ſtands ore <hi>Him</hi> for a <hi>Hearſe,</hi> and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Reſurrection</hi> for <hi>His Epitaph.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98172:54"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the death of my ever deſired friend Doctor Donne Dean of Pauls.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO have liv'd eminent in a degreee</l>
                  <l>Beyond our lofty'ſt flights, that is like thee;</l>
                  <l>Or t'have had too much merit is not ſafe;</l>
                  <l>For ſuch exceſſes find no Epitaph.</l>
                  <l>At common graves we have Poetick eyes</l>
                  <l>Can melt themſelves in eaſie Elegies;</l>
                  <l>Each quill can drop his tributary verſe,</l>
                  <l>And pin it with the Hatchments, to the Herſe:</l>
                  <l>But at thine, Poem or inſcription</l>
                  <l>(Rich Soul of wit and language:) we have none;</l>
                  <l>Indeed a ſilence does that Tomb befit</l>
                  <l>Where is no Herald left to blazon it.</l>
                  <l>Widdow'd invention juſtly doth forbear</l>
                  <l>To come abroad knowing thou art not here,</l>
                  <l>Late her great Patron; whoſe prerogative</l>
                  <l>Maintain'd and cloth'd her ſo, as none alive</l>
                  <l>Muſt now preſume to keep her at thy rate,</l>
                  <l>Though he the Indies for her dowre eſtate:</l>
                  <l>Or elſe that awful fire, which once did burn</l>
                  <l>In thy clear brain, now fall'n into thy Urn.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:98172:55"/>Lives there to fright rude Empericks from thence,</l>
                  <l>Which might profane thee by their ignorance:</l>
                  <l>Who ever writes of thee, and in a ſtyle</l>
                  <l>Unworthy ſuch a Theme, does but revile</l>
                  <l>Thy precious duſt, and wake a learned ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Which may revenge his rapes upon thy merit.</l>
                  <l>For all a low-pitcht fancie can deviſe,</l>
                  <l>Will prove at beſt but hallow'd injuries.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou, like the dying Swan, didſt lately ſing</l>
                  <l>Thy mournful Dirge in audience of the King;</l>
                  <l>When pale looks, and faint accents of thy breath,</l>
                  <l>Preſented ſo to life that piece of death,</l>
                  <l>That it was fear'd and propheſi'd by all</l>
                  <l>Thou thither cam'ſt to preach thy Funerall.</l>
                  <l>O! hadſt thou in an Elegiack knell</l>
                  <l>Rung out unto the world thine own farewell;</l>
                  <l>And in thy high victorious numbers beat</l>
                  <l>The ſolemn meaſure of thy griev'd retreat:</l>
                  <l>Thou might'ſt the Poets ſervice now have miſt,</l>
                  <l>As well as then thou didſt prevent the Prieſt:</l>
                  <l>And never to the world beholden be,</l>
                  <l>So much as for an Epitaph for thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:98172:55"/>
                  <l>I do not like the office. Nor is't fit</l>
                  <l>Thou, who didſt lend our age ſuch ſummes of wit,</l>
                  <l>Should'ſt now reborrow from her Bankrupt Mine</l>
                  <l>That Ore to bury thee, which once was thine.</l>
                  <l>Rather ſtill leave us in thy debt; and know</l>
                  <l>(Exalted Soul!) More glory 'tis to ow</l>
                  <l>Unto thy Herſe what we can never pay,</l>
                  <l>Then with embaſed coin thoſe Rites defray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Commit we then Thee to Thy Self: nor blame</l>
                  <l>Our drooping loves, which thus to thine own fame</l>
                  <l>Leave Thee Executour: ſince but thy own</l>
                  <l>No pen could do Thee Juſtice, nor Bayes crown</l>
                  <l>Thy vaſt deſert; ſave that we nothing can</l>
                  <l>Depute to be thy aſhes Guardian.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So Jewellers no Art or Metal truſt</l>
                  <l>To form the Diamond, but the Diamonds duſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:98172:64"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the moſt victorious King of Sweden Guſtavus Adolphus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke a cold fatal ſweat which uſhers death</l>
                  <l>My thoughts hang on me, &amp; my lab'ring breath</l>
                  <l>Stopt up with ſighs, my fancie big with woes,</l>
                  <l>Feels two twinn'd mountains ſtruggle in her throws,</l>
                  <l>Of boundleſs ſorrow one, t'other of ſin;</l>
                  <l>For leſs let no one rate it to begin</l>
                  <l>Where honour ends. In Great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> flame</l>
                  <l>That ſtyle burnt out, and waſted to a name,</l>
                  <l>Does barely live with us. As when the ſnuff.</l>
                  <l>That fed it failes, the Taper turns to ſnuff.</l>
                  <l>With this poor ſnuff, this ayerie ſhadow, we</l>
                  <l>Of Fame and Honour muſt contented be;</l>
                  <l>Since from the vain graſp of our wiſhes fled</l>
                  <l>Their glorious ſubſtance is, now <hi>He</hi> is dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Speak it again, and louder, louder yet;</l>
                  <l>Elſe whil'ſt we hear the ſound we ſhall forget</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:98172:64"/>What it delivers. Let hoarſe rumor cry</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe ſo many ecchoes multiply,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe may like num'rous witneſſes confute</l>
                  <l>Our unbelieving ſoules, that would diſpute</l>
                  <l>And doubt this truth for ever. This one way</l>
                  <l>Is left our incredulity to ſway;</l>
                  <l>To waken our deaf ſenſe, and make our ears</l>
                  <l>As open and dilated as our fears;</l>
                  <l>That we may feel the blow, and feeling grieve,</l>
                  <l>At what we would not feign, but muſt believe.</l>
                  <l>And in that horrid faith behold the world</l>
                  <l>From her proud height of expectation hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>Stooping with him, as if ſhe ſtrove to have</l>
                  <l>No lower Center now then <hi>Swedens</hi> grave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O could not all thy purchas'd victories</l>
                  <l>Like to thy Fame thy Fleſh immortalize?</l>
                  <l>Were not thy vertue nor thy valour charmes</l>
                  <l>To guard thy body from thoſe outward harmes</l>
                  <l>Which could not reach thy ſoul? could not thy ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Lend ſomewhat which thy frailty might inherit</l>
                  <l>From thy diviner part, that Death nor Hate</l>
                  <l>Nor envy's bullets ere could penetrate?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:98172:56"/>Could not thy early Trophies in ſtern fight</l>
                  <l>Torn from the <hi>Dane,</hi> the <hi>Pole,</hi> the <hi>Moſcovite?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which were thy triumphs ſeeds, as pledges ſown,</l>
                  <l>That when thy honours harveſt was ripe grown,</l>
                  <l>With full-ſumm'd wing thou Falcon-like wouldſt fly</l>
                  <l>And cuff the <hi>Eagle</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> sky:</l>
                  <l>Forcing his iron beak and feathers feel</l>
                  <l>They were not proof 'gainſt thy victorious ſteel.</l>
                  <l>Could not all theſe protect thee? or prevaile</l>
                  <l>To fright that Coward Death, who oft grew pale</l>
                  <l>To look thee and thy battails in the face?</l>
                  <l>Alas they could not: Deſtiny gives place</l>
                  <l>To none; nor is it ſeen that Princes lives</l>
                  <l>Can ſaved be by their prerogatives.</l>
                  <l>No more was thine; who clos'd in thy cold lead,</l>
                  <l>Doſt from thy ſelf a mournful lecture read</l>
                  <l>Of Mans ſhort-dated glory: learn you Kings,</l>
                  <l>You are like him but penetrable things;</l>
                  <l>Though you from Demi-Gods derive your birth,</l>
                  <l>You are at beſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t honourable earth:</l>
                  <l>And howere ſiſted from that courſer bran</l>
                  <l>Which does compound and knead the common man,</l>
                  <l>Nothing's immortal or from earth refin'd</l>
                  <l>About you, but your <hi>Office</hi> and your <hi>Mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:98172:56"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere then break your falſe Glaſſes, which preſent</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou greater then your <hi>Maker</hi> ever meant:</l>
                  <l>Make truth your Mirrour now, ſince you find all</l>
                  <l>That flatter you confuted by his fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſince it was decreed thy lifes bright Sun</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt be eclips'd ere thy full courſe was run,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e proud thou didſt in thy black Obſequies</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith greater glory ſet then others riſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or in thy death, as life, thou heldeſt one</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt juſt and regular proportion.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ook how the Circles drawn by Compaſs meet</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndiviſibly joyned head to feet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd by continued points which them unite</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>row at once Circular and Infinite:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> did thy Fate and honour now contend</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o match thy brave beginning with thy end.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herefore thou hadſt inſtead of Paſſing bells</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Drums and Cannons thunder for thy knells;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd in the Field thou did'ſt triumphing dy,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſing thy eye-lids with a victory:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat ſo by thouſands who there loſt their breath</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing-like</hi> thou might'ſt be waited on in death.</l>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:98172:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:98172:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:98172:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:98172:58"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98172:59"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:98172:59"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:98172:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98172:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:98172:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:98172:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98172:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:98172:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:98172:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:98172:63"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:98172:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:98172:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:98172:66"/>
                  <l>Liv'd Plutarch now, and would of Caeſar tell,</l>
                  <l>He could make none but <hi>Thee</hi> his parallel;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe tide of glory ſwelling to the brim</l>
                  <l>Needs borrow no addition from <hi>Him.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When did great Julius in any Clime</l>
                  <l>Atchieve ſo much and in ſo ſmall a time?</l>
                  <l>Or if he did, yet ſhalt <hi>Thou</hi> in that land</l>
                  <l>Single for him and unexampled ſtand.</l>
                  <l>When ore the Germans firſt his Eagle towr'd</l>
                  <l>What ſaw the Legions which on them he pour'd?</l>
                  <l>But maſſie bodies, made their ſwords to try</l>
                  <l>Subjects not for his fight<note place="margin">Magis iumphati uam icti. <hi>acit. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or. Ger.</hi>
                     </note>, but ſlavery.</l>
                  <l>In that ſo vaſt expanded peece of ground</l>
                  <l>(Now Swedens Theater and Tomb) he found</l>
                  <l>Nothing worth <hi>Caeſars</hi> valour, or his fear,</l>
                  <l>No conqu'ring Army, nor a <hi>Tilley</hi> there,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtrength nor wiles, nor practice in the wan</l>
                  <l>Might the fierce Torrent of thy triumphs barre,</l>
                  <l>But that thy winged ſword twice made him yield,</l>
                  <l>Both from his trenches beat, and from the field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſides the <hi>Romane</hi> thought he had done much</l>
                  <l>Did he the bank of <hi>Rhenus</hi> onely touch.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:98172:66"/>But though his march was bounded by the <hi>Rhine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Oder</hi> nor the <hi>Danube Thee</hi> confine;</l>
                  <l>And but thy frailty did thy fame prevent,</l>
                  <l>Thou hadſt thy conqueſts ſtrecht to ſuch extent,</l>
                  <l>Thou might'ſt <hi>Vienna</hi> reach, and after ſpan</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Mulda</hi> to the <hi>Baltick Ocean.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But death hath ſpann'd thee: nor muſt we divine</l>
                  <l>What heir thou leav'ſt to finiſh thy deſign,</l>
                  <l>Or who ſhall thee ſucceed as Champion</l>
                  <l>For liberty and for religion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy task is done; as in a Watch the ſpring</l>
                  <l>Wound to the height, relaxes with the ſtring:</l>
                  <l>So thy ſteel nerves of conqueſt, from their ſteep</l>
                  <l>Aſcent declin'd, lie ſlackt in thy laſt ſleep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reſt then triumphant ſoul! for ever reſt!</l>
                  <l>And, like the Phoenix in her ſpicy neſt,</l>
                  <l>Embalm'd with thine own merit, upward fly,</l>
                  <l>Born in a cloud of perfume to the sky.</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt, as in deathleſs Urnes, each noble mind</l>
                  <l>Treaſures thy aſhes which are left behind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:98172:67"/>
                  <l>And if perhaps no <hi>Caſſiopeian</hi> ſpark</l>
                  <l>(Which in the North did thy firſt riſing mark)</l>
                  <l>Shine ore thy Herſe: the breath of our juſt praiſe</l>
                  <l>Shall to the Firmament thy vertues raiſe;</l>
                  <l>Then fix, and kindle them into a Starre,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe influence may crown thy glorious warre.</l>
               </lg>
               <q>
                  <l>—O Famâ ingens ingentior armis</l>
                  <l>Rex Guſtave, quibus Coelo te laudibus aequem?</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Virgil. Aeneid.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:98172:67"/>
               <head>To my Noble and Judicious Friend Sir Henry Blount upon his Voyage.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SIR, I muſt ever own my ſelf to be</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt with humane curioſitie</l>
                  <l>Of ſeeing all that might the ſenſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>By thoſe two baits of profit and delight:</l>
                  <l>And ſince I had the wit to underſtand</l>
                  <l>The terms of Native or of forreign land;</l>
                  <l>I have had ſtrong and oft deſires to tread</l>
                  <l>Some of thoſe voyages which I have read.</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill ſo fruitleſs have my wiſhes prov'd,</l>
                  <l>That from my Countreys ſmoke I never mov'd:</l>
                  <l>Nor ever had the fortune (though deſign'd)</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie the wandrings of my mind.</l>
                  <l>Therefore at laſt I did with ſome content,</l>
                  <l>Beguile my ſelf in time, which others ſpent;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe art to Provinces ſmall lines allots,</l>
                  <l>And repreſents large Kingdomes but in ſpots.</l>
                  <l>Thus by <hi>Ortelius</hi> and <hi>Mercators</hi> aid</l>
                  <l>Through moſt of the diſcover'd world I ſtrai'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:98172:68"/>I could with eaſe double the <hi>Southern cape,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in my paſſage <hi>Affricks</hi> wonders take:</l>
                  <l>Then with a ſpeed proportion'd to the Scale</l>
                  <l>Northward again, as high as <hi>Zemla</hi> ſayl.</l>
                  <l>Oft hath the travel of my eye outrun</l>
                  <l>(Though I ſat ſtill) the journey of the Sun:</l>
                  <l>Yet made an end, ere his declining beams</l>
                  <l>Did night <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uench themſelves in <hi>Thetis</hi> ſtreams.</l>
                  <l>Oft have I gone through Aegypt in a day,</l>
                  <l>Not hinder'd by the droughts of Lybia;</l>
                  <l>In which, for lack of water tides of ſand</l>
                  <l>By a dry deluge overflow the land.</l>
                  <l>There I the <hi>Pyramids</hi> and <hi>Cairo</hi> ſee,</l>
                  <l>Still famous for the warres of <hi>Tomombee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And its own greatneſs; whoſe immured fence</l>
                  <l>Takes fourty miles in the circumference.</l>
                  <l>Then without guide, or ſtronger Caravan</l>
                  <l>Which might ſecure the wild Arabian,</l>
                  <l>Back through the ſcorched Deſarts paſs, to ſeek</l>
                  <l>Once the worlds Lord, now the beſlaved <hi>Greek,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made by a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> yoak and fortunes hate</l>
                  <l>In language as in mind, degenerate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:98172:68"/>
                  <l>And here all wrapt in pity and amaze</l>
                  <l>I ſtand, whil'ſt I upon the Sultan gaze;</l>
                  <l>To think how he with pride and rapine fir'd</l>
                  <l>So vaſt a Territory hath acquir'd;</l>
                  <l>And by what daring ſteps he did become</l>
                  <l>The Aſian fear, and ſcoarge of Chriſtendome:</l>
                  <l>How he atchiev'd, and kept, and by what arts</l>
                  <l>He did concencer thoſe divided parts;</l>
                  <l>And how he holds that monſtrous bulk in aw,</l>
                  <l>By ſetled rules of tyrannie, not Law:</l>
                  <l>So Rivers large and rapid ſtreams began,</l>
                  <l>Swelling from drops into an Ocean.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sure who ere ſhall the juſt extraction bring</l>
                  <l>Of this Gigantick power from the ſpring;</l>
                  <l>Muſt there confeſs a higher Ordinance</l>
                  <l>Did it for terrour to the earth advance.</l>
                  <l>For mark how 'mongſt a lawleſs ſtraggling crew</l>
                  <l>Made up of <hi>Arab, Saracen,</hi> and <hi>Jew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The worlds diſturber, faithleſs <hi>Mahomet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did by Impoſtures an opinion get:</l>
                  <l>O're whom he firſt uſurps as Prince, and than</l>
                  <l>As Prophet does obtrude his <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:98172:69"/>Next, how fierce <hi>Ottoman</hi> his claim made good</l>
                  <l>From that unbleſt Religion, by blood;</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt he the Eaſtern Kingdomes did deface,</l>
                  <l>To make their ruine his proud Empires baſe.</l>
                  <l>Then like a Comet blazing in the skies,</l>
                  <l>How Death-portending <hi>Amurath</hi> did riſe,</l>
                  <l>When he his horned Creſcents did diſplay</l>
                  <l>Upon the fatal Plains of <hi>Servia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And farther ſtill his ſanguin treſſes ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Croya</hi> Life and Conqueſts limited.</l>
                  <l>Laſtly, how <hi>Mahomet</hi> thence ſtyl'd the <hi>Great,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Conſtantines</hi> his own Imperial Seat;</l>
                  <l>After that he in one victorious bond</l>
                  <l>Two Empires graſpt, of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Trabezond.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, and much more then this, I gladly read,</l>
                  <l>Where my relators it had ſtoryed;</l>
                  <l>Beſides that Peoples Manners and their Rites,</l>
                  <l>Their warlike diſcipline and order'd fights;</l>
                  <l>Their deſp'rate valour, hardned by the ſence</l>
                  <l>Of unavoided Fate and Providence:</l>
                  <l>Their habit, and their houſes, who confer</l>
                  <l>Leſs coſt on them then on their Sepulchre:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:98172:69"/>Their frequent waſhings, and the ſeveral Bath</l>
                  <l>Each <hi>Meſchit</hi> to it ſelf annexed hath:</l>
                  <l>What honour they unto the <hi>Mufty</hi> give,</l>
                  <l>What to the <hi>Soveraign</hi> under whom they live:</l>
                  <l>What quarter Chriſtians have; how juſt and free</l>
                  <l>To inoffenſive Travellers they be:</l>
                  <l>Though I confeſs, like ſtomacks fed with news,</l>
                  <l>I took them in for wonder, not for uſe,</l>
                  <l>Till your experienc'd and authentick pen</l>
                  <l>Taught me to know the places and the men;</l>
                  <l>And made all thoſe ſuſpected truths become</l>
                  <l>Undoubted now, and cleer as Axiom.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sir, for this work more then my thanks is due,</l>
                  <l>I am at once inform'd and cur'd by you.</l>
                  <l>So that, were I aſſur'd I ſhould live o're</l>
                  <l>My periods of time run out before;</l>
                  <l>Nere needed my erratick wiſh tranſport</l>
                  <l>Me from my Native liſts to that reſort,</l>
                  <l>Where many at outlandiſh Marts unlade</l>
                  <l>Ingenuous manners, and do onely trade</l>
                  <l>For vices and the language. By your eyes</l>
                  <l>I here have made my full diſcoveries;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:98172:70"/>And all your Countreys ſo exactly ſeen,</l>
                  <l>As in the voyage I had ſharer been.</l>
                  <l>By this you make me ſo; and the whole land</l>
                  <l>Your debtour: which can onely underſtand</l>
                  <l>How much ſhe owes you, when her ſons ſhall try</l>
                  <l>The ſolid depths of your rare hiſtory,</l>
                  <l>Which looks above our gadders trivial reach,</l>
                  <l>The Common Place of travellers, who teach</l>
                  <l>But Table-talk; and ſeldomly aſpire</l>
                  <l>Beyond the Countres Dyet or Attire;</l>
                  <l>Whereas your piercing judgement does relate</l>
                  <l>The Policy and Manage of each State.</l>
                  <l>And ſince ſhe muſt here without envy grant</l>
                  <l>That you have further journey'd the <hi>Levant</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then any noble ſpirit by her bred</l>
                  <l>Hath in your way as yet adventured;</l>
                  <l>I cannot leſs in juſtice from her look,</l>
                  <l>Then that ſhe henceforth Canonize your book</l>
                  <l>A Rule to all her travellers, and you</l>
                  <l>The brave example; from whoſe equal view</l>
                  <l>Each knowing Reader may himſelf direct,</l>
                  <l>How he may go abroad to ſome effect,</l>
                  <l>And not for form: what diſtance and what truſt</l>
                  <l>In thoſe remoter parts obſerve he muſt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:98172:70"/>How he with jealous people may converſe,</l>
                  <l>Yet take no hurt himſelf by that commerce.</l>
                  <l>So when he ſhall imbark'd in dangers be,</l>
                  <l>Which wit and wary caution not foreſee;</l>
                  <l>If he partake your valour and your brain,</l>
                  <l>He may perhaps come ſafely off again,</l>
                  <l>As you have done; though not ſo richly fraught</l>
                  <l>As this return hath to our Staple brought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I know your modeſty ſhuns vulgar praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And I have none to bring: but onely raiſe</l>
                  <l>This monument of Honour and of Love,</l>
                  <l>Which your long known deſerts ſo far improve,</l>
                  <l>They leave me doubtfull in what ſtyle to end,</l>
                  <l>Whether more your admirer or your friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:98172:71"/>
               <head>To my honoured Friend Mr. <hi>George Sandys.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IT is, Sir, a confeſt intruſion here</l>
                  <l>That I before your labours do appear,</l>
                  <l>Which no loud Herald need, that may proclaim</l>
                  <l>Or ſeek acceptance, but the Authors fame.</l>
                  <l>Much leſs that ſhould this happy work commend,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſubject is its licence, and doth ſend</l>
                  <l>It to the world to be receiv'd and read,</l>
                  <l>Far as the glorious beams of truth are ſpread.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor let it be imagin'd that I look</l>
                  <l>Onely with Cuſtomes eye upon your book;</l>
                  <l>Or in this ſervice that 'twas my intent</l>
                  <l>T'exclude your perſon from your argument:</l>
                  <l>I ſhall profeſs much of the love I ow,</l>
                  <l>Doth from the root of our extraction grow;</l>
                  <l>To which though I can little contribute,</l>
                  <l>Yet with a naturall joy I muſt impute</l>
                  <l>To our Tribes honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, what by you is done</l>
                  <l>Worthy the title of a <hi>Prelates</hi> ſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:98172:71"/>
                  <l>And ſcarcely have two brothers farther borne</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Fathers name, or with more value worne</l>
                  <l>Their own, then two of you; whoſe pens and feet</l>
                  <l>Have made the diſtant Points of Heav'n to meet;</l>
                  <l>He by exact diſcoveries of the<note n="*" place="margin">Sr. Edw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sandys ſurvay of religion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Weſt.</note> Weſt,</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf by painful travels in the Eaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some more like you might pow'rfully confute</l>
                  <l>Th'oppoſers of Prieſts marriage by the fruit.</l>
                  <l>And (ſince tis known for all their ſtreight vow'd life,</l>
                  <l>They like the ſex in any ſtyle but wife)</l>
                  <l>Cauſe them to change their Cloyſter for that State</l>
                  <l>Which keeps men chaſte by vowes legitimate:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or ſhame to father their relations,</l>
                  <l>Or under Nephews names diſguiſe their ſons.</l>
                  <l>This Child of yours born without ſpurious blot,</l>
                  <l>And fairly Midwiv'd as it was begot,</l>
                  <l>Doth ſo much of the Parents goodneſs wear,</l>
                  <l>You may be proud to own it for your Heir.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe choice acquits you from the common ſin</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch, who finiſh worſe then they begin:</l>
                  <l>You mend upon your ſelf, and your laſt ſtrain</l>
                  <l>Does of your firſt the ſtart in judgment gain;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:98172:72"/>Since what in curious travel was begun,</l>
                  <l>You here conclude in a devotion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where in delightful raptures we deſcry</l>
                  <l>As in a Map, <hi>Sions Chorography</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Laid out in ſo direct and ſmooth a line,</l>
                  <l>Men need not go about through Paleſtine:</l>
                  <l>Who ſeek Chriſt here will the ſtreight Rode prefer</l>
                  <l>As neerer much then by the Sepulchre.</l>
                  <l>For not a limb growes here, but is a path;</l>
                  <l>Which in Gods City the bleſt Center hath:</l>
                  <l>And doth ſo ſweetly on each paſſion ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>The moſt fantaſtick taſte will ſomewhat like.</l>
                  <l>To the unquiet ſoul <hi>Job</hi> ſtill from hence</l>
                  <l>Pleads in th'example of his patience.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ob.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The mortify'd may hear the wiſe King preach,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cl ſiaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When his repentance made him fit to teach.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall the ſinging Siſters be content</l>
                  <l>To chant at home the Act of Parliament,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re Act of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arliament <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ks gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>th of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mb. ſet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tune by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Dod a tradeſman of London, at the end of his Pſalmes, which ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>om the Preſs <hi>Anno Domini 1620.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Turn'd out of reaſon into rhime by one</l>
                  <l>Free of his tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de, though not of Helicon,</l>
                  <l>Who did in his Poetick zeal contend</l>
                  <l>Others edition by a worſe to mend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:98172:72"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere are choice Hymnes and Carolls for the glad,<note place="margin">Hymns Lament at. Pſalmes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith melancholy Dirges for the ſad:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd <hi>David</hi> (as he could his skill transfer)</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaks like himſelf by an interpreter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Muſe rekindled hath the Prophets fire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd tun'd the ſtrings of his neglected Lyre;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aking the Note and Duty ſo agree,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey now become a perfect harmonie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, I have long wiſht to ſee</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Pſalmes reduc'd to this conformity:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieving the ſongs of Sion ſhould be ſung</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> phraſe not diff'ring from a barbarous tongue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f, by cuſtome warranted, we may</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g that to God we would be loth to ſay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r be it from my purpoſe to upbraid</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eir honeſt meaning, who firſt offer made</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at book in Meeter to compile, which you</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve mended in the form, and built a new:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d it was well, conſidering the time,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich hardly could diſtinguiſh verſe and rhime,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t now the language, like the Church, hath won</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re luſtre ſince the Reformation;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:98172:73"/>None can condemn the wiſh or labour ſpent</l>
                  <l>Good matter in good words to repreſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet in this jealous age ſome ſuch there be,</l>
                  <l>So without cauſe afraid of novelty,</l>
                  <l>They would not (were it in their pow'r to chooſe)</l>
                  <l>An old ill practiſe for a better loſe.</l>
                  <l>Men who a ruſtick plainneſſe ſo affect,</l>
                  <l>They think God ſerved beſt by their neglect.</l>
                  <l>Holding the cauſe would be profan'd by it,</l>
                  <l>Were they at charge of learning or of wit.</l>
                  <l>And therefore bluntly (what comes next) they brin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Courſe and unſtudy'd ſtuffs for offering;</l>
                  <l>Which like th'old Tabernacles cov'ring are,</l>
                  <l>Made up of Badgers skins, and of Goats haire.</l>
                  <l>But theſe are Paradoxes they muſt uſe</l>
                  <l>Their ſloth and bolder ignorance t'excuſe.</l>
                  <l>Who would not laugh at one will naked go,</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe in old hangings truth is pictur'd ſo?</l>
                  <l>Though plainneſs be reputed honours note,</l>
                  <l>They mantles uſe to beautify the coat;</l>
                  <l>So that a curious (unaffected) dreſs</l>
                  <l>Addes much unto the bodies comelineſs:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:98172:73"/>And whereſoere the ſubjects beſt, the ſence</l>
                  <l>Is better'd by the ſpeakers eloquence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, Sir, to you I ſhall no trophee raiſe</l>
                  <l>From other mens detraction or diſraiſe:</l>
                  <l>That Jewel never had inherent worth,</l>
                  <l>Which askt ſuch foils as theſe to ſet it forth.</l>
                  <l>If any quarrel your attempt or ſtyle,</l>
                  <l>Forgive them; their own folly they revile.</l>
                  <l>Since, 'gainſt themſelves, their factious envy ſhall</l>
                  <l>Allow this work of yours Canonicall.</l>
                  <l>Nor may you fear the Poets common lot,</l>
                  <l>Read, and commended, and then quite forgot:</l>
                  <l>The brazen Mines and Marble Rocks ſhall waſt,</l>
                  <l>When your foundation will unſhaken laſt.</l>
                  <l>'Tis fames beſt pay, that you your labours ſee</l>
                  <l>By their immortal ſubject crowned be.</l>
                  <l>For nere was writer in oblivion hid</l>
                  <l>Who firm'd his name on ſuch a Pyramid.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:98172:74"/>
               <head>The Woes of Eſay.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVOe to the worldly men whoſe covetous</l>
                  <l>Ambition labours to joyn houſe to houſe,</l>
                  <l>Lay field to field, till their incloſures edge</l>
                  <l>The Plain, girdling a countrey with one hedge:</l>
                  <l>That leave no place unbought, no piece of earth</l>
                  <l>Which they will not ingroſs, making a dearth</l>
                  <l>Of all inhabitants, untill they ſtand</l>
                  <l>Unneighbour'd as unbleſt within their land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſin cryes in Gods ear, who hath decreed</l>
                  <l>The ground they ſow ſhall not return the ſeed.</l>
                  <l>They that unpeopled countreys to create</l>
                  <l>Themſelves ſole Lords, made many deſolate</l>
                  <l>To build up their own houſe, ſhall find at laſt</l>
                  <l>Ruine and fearful deſolation caſt</l>
                  <l>Upon themſelves. Their Manſion ſhall become</l>
                  <l>A Deſart, and their Palace prove a tombe.</l>
                  <l>Their vines ſhall barren be, their land yield tares;</l>
                  <l>Their houſe ſhall have no dwellers, they no heires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:98172:74"/>
                  <l>Woe unto thoſe that with the morning Sun</l>
                  <l>Riſe to drink wine, and ſit till he have run</l>
                  <l>His weary courſe; not ceaſing untill night</l>
                  <l>Have quencht their underſtanding with the light:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe raging thirſt, like fire, will not be tam'd,</l>
                  <l>The more they poure the more they are inflam'd.</l>
                  <l>Woe unto them that onely mighty are</l>
                  <l>To wage with wine; in which unhappy war</l>
                  <l>They who the glory of the day have won,</l>
                  <l>Muſt yield them foil'd and vanquiſht by the tun.</l>
                  <l>Men that live thus, as if they liv'd in jeſt,</l>
                  <l>Fooling their time with Muſick and a feaſt;</l>
                  <l>That did exile all ſounds from their ſoft ear</l>
                  <l>But of the harp, muſt this ſad diſcord hear</l>
                  <l>Compos'd in threats. The feet which meaſures tread</l>
                  <l>Shall in captivity be fettered:</l>
                  <l>Famine ſhall ſcourge them for their vaſt exceſs;</l>
                  <l>And Hell revenge their monſtrous drunkenneſs;</l>
                  <l>Which hath enlarg'd it ſelf to ſwallow ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe throats nere knew enough, though ſtill too much</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Woe unto thoſe that countenance a ſin,</l>
                  <l>Siding with vice that it may credit win.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:98172:75"/>By their unhallow'd vote: that do benight</l>
                  <l>The truth with errour, putting dark for light,</l>
                  <l>And light for dark; that call an evil good,</l>
                  <l>And would by vice have vertue underſtood:</l>
                  <l>That with their frown can ſowre an honeſt cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Or ſweeten any bad by their applauſe.</l>
                  <l>That juſtify the wicked for reward;</l>
                  <l>And void of morall goodneſs or regard,</l>
                  <l>Plot with detraction to traduce the fame</l>
                  <l>Of him whoſe merit hath enroll'd his name</l>
                  <l>Among the juſt. Therefore Gods vengeful ire</l>
                  <l>Glows on his people, and becomes a fire</l>
                  <l>Whoſe greedy and exalted flame ſhall burn,</l>
                  <l>Till they like ſtraw or chaffe to nothing turn.</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they have rebell'd againſt the right,</l>
                  <l>To God and Law perverſly oppoſite,</l>
                  <l>As Plants which Sun nor ſhowres did ever bleſs,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall their root convert to rottenneſs;</l>
                  <l>And their ſucceſſions bud, in which they truſt,</l>
                  <l>Shall (like <hi>Gomorrahs</hi> fruit) moulder to duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Woe unto thoſe that drunk with ſelf-conceit,</l>
                  <l>Value their own deſiggs at ſuch a rate</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:98172:75"/>Which humane wiſdome cannot reach; that ſit</l>
                  <l>Enthron'd, as ſole Monopoliſts of wit:</l>
                  <l>That out-look reaſon, and ſuppoſe the eye</l>
                  <l>Of Nature blind to their diſcovery,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt they a title make to underſtand</l>
                  <l>What ever ſecret's boſom'd in the land.</l>
                  <l>But God ſhall imp their pride, and let them ſee</l>
                  <l>They are but fools in a ſublime degree:</l>
                  <l>He ſhall bring down and humble thoſe proud eyes,</l>
                  <l>In which falſe glaſſes onely they lookt wiſe:</l>
                  <l>That all the world may laugh, and learn by it,</l>
                  <l>There is no folly to pretended wit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Woe unto thoſe that draw iniquity</l>
                  <l>With cords, and by a vain ſecurity</l>
                  <l>Lengthen the ſinful trace, till their own chain</l>
                  <l>Of many links form'd by laborious pain,</l>
                  <l>Do pull them into Hell; that as with lines</l>
                  <l>And Cart-ropes drag on their unwilling crimes:</l>
                  <l>Who, rather then they will commit no ſin,</l>
                  <l>Tempt all occaſions to let it in.</l>
                  <l>As if there were no God, who muſt exact</l>
                  <l>The ſtrict account for e'ry vicious fact;</l>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:98172:76"/>
               <head>An Eſſay on Death and a Priſon.</head>
               <l>A Priſon is in all things like a grave,</l>
               <l>Where we no better priviledges have</l>
               <l>Then dead men, nor ſo good. The ſoul once fled</l>
               <l>Lives freer now, then when ſhe was cloyſtered</l>
               <l>In walls of fleſh; and though ſhe organs want</l>
               <l>To act her ſwift deſigns, yet all will grant</l>
               <l>Her faculties more clear, now ſeparate,</l>
               <l>Then if the ſame conjunction, which of late</l>
               <l>Did marry her to earth, had ſtood in force,</l>
               <l>Uncapable of death, or of divorce:</l>
               <l>But an impriſon'd mind, though living, dies,</l>
               <l>And at one time feels two captivities;</l>
               <l>A narrow dungeon which her body holds,</l>
               <l>But narrower body which her ſelf enfolds.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt I in priſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, nothing is free,</l>
               <l>Nothing enlarg'd but thought and miſerie;</l>
               <l>Though e'ry chink be ſtopt, the doors cloſe barr'd,</l>
               <l>Deſpight of walls and locks, through e'ry ward</l>
               <l>Theſe have their iſſues forth; may take the aire,</l>
               <l>Though not for health, but onely to compare</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:98172:76"/>How wretched thoſe men are who freedom want,</l>
               <l>By ſuch as never ſuffer'd a reſtraint.</l>
               <l>In which unquiet travel could I find</l>
               <l>Ought that might ſettle my diſtemper'd mind,</l>
               <l>Or of ſome comfort make diſcovery</l>
               <l>It were a voyage well imploy'd: but I,</l>
               <l>Like our raw travellers that croſs the ſeas</l>
               <l>To fetch home faſhions or ſome worſe diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Inſtead of quiet a new torture bring</l>
               <l>Home t'afflict me, malice and murmuring.</l>
               <l>What is't I envy not? no dog nor fly</l>
               <l>But my deſires prefer, and wiſh were I;</l>
               <l>For they are free, or if they were like me,</l>
               <l>They had no ſenſe to know calamitie.</l>
               <l>But in the grave no ſparks of envy live,</l>
               <l>No hot compariſons that cauſes give</l>
               <l>Of quarrel, or that our affections move</l>
               <l>Any condition, ſave their own, to love.</l>
               <l>There are no objects there but ſhades and night,</l>
               <l>And yet that darkneſs better then the light.</l>
               <l>There lives a ſilent harmony, no jar</l>
               <l>Or diſcord can that ſweet ſoft conſort mar.</l>
               <l>The graves deaf ear is clos'd againſt all noiſe</l>
               <l>Save that which rocks muſt hear, the angels voice:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:98172:77"/>Whoſe trump ſhall wake the world, and raiſe up men</l>
               <l>Who in earths boſom ſlept, bed-rid till then.</l>
               <l>What man then would, who on deaths pillow ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</l>
               <l>Be re-inſpir'd with life, though golden numbers</l>
               <l>Of bliſs were pour'd into his breaſt; though he</l>
               <l>Were ſure in change to gain a Monarchies</l>
               <l>A Monarchs glorious ſtate compar'd with his,</l>
               <l>Leſs ſafe, leſs free, leſs firm, leſs quiet is.</l>
               <l>For nere was any Prince advanc't ſo high</l>
               <l>That he was out of reach of miſery:</l>
               <l>Never did ſtory yet a law report</l>
               <l>To baniſh fate or ſorrow from his Court;</l>
               <l>Where ere he moves by land, or through the Main,</l>
               <l>Theſe go along ſworn members of his train.</l>
               <l>But he whom the kind earth hath entertain'd,</l>
               <l>Hath in her womb a ſanctuary gain'd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe charter and protection arm him ſo,</l>
               <l>That he is priviledg'd from future woe.</l>
               <l>The Coffin's a ſafe harbour, where he rides</l>
               <l>Land-bound, below croſs windes, or churliſh tides.</l>
               <l>For grief, ſprung up with life, was mans half-brother</l>
               <l>Fed by the taſte, brought forth by ſin, the mother.</l>
               <l>And ſince the firſt ſeduction of the wife,</l>
               <l>God did decree to grief a leaſe for life;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:98172:77"/>Which Patent in full force continue muſt,</l>
               <l>Till man that diſobey'd revert to duſt.</l>
               <l>So that lifes ſorrows ratifi'd by God</l>
               <l>Cannot expire, or find their period,</l>
               <l>Untill the ſoul and body diſunite,</l>
               <l>And by two diff'rent wayes from each take flight.</l>
               <l>But they diſſolved once our woes disband,</l>
               <l>Th'aſſurance cancell'd by one fatall hand;</l>
               <l>Soon as the paſſing bell proclaims me dead,</l>
               <l>My ſorrows ſink with me, lye buried</l>
               <l>In the ſame heap of duſt, the ſelf-ſame Urn</l>
               <l>Doth them and me alike to nothing turn.</l>
               <l>If then of theſe I might election make</l>
               <l>Whether I would refuſe, and whether take,</l>
               <l>Rather then like a ſullen Anchorite</l>
               <l>I would live cas'd in ſtone, and learn to write</l>
               <l>A <hi>Priſoners ſtory,</hi> which might ſteal ſome tears</l>
               <l>From the ſad eyes of him that reads or hears;</l>
               <l>Give me a peaceful death, and let me meet</l>
               <l>My freedom ſeal'd up in my winding ſheet.</l>
               <l>Death is the pledge of reſt, and with one bayl</l>
               <l>Two Priſons quits, the Body and the Jayl.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:98172:78"/>
               <head>The Labyrinth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIfe is a crooked Labyrinth, and we</l>
                  <l>Are daily loſt in that Obliquity.</l>
                  <l>'Tis a perplexed circle, in whoſe round</l>
                  <l>Nothing but ſorrows and new ſins abound.</l>
                  <l>How is the faint impreſſion of each good</l>
                  <l>Drown'd in the vicious Channel of our blood?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Ebbes and tides by their viciſſitude</l>
                  <l>Both our great Maker and our ſelves delude.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O wherefore is the moſt diſcerning eye</l>
                  <l>Unapt to make its own diſcovery?</l>
                  <l>Why is the cleareſt and beſt judging mind</l>
                  <l>In her own ills prevention dark and blind?</l>
                  <l>Dull to adviſe, to act precipitate,</l>
                  <l>We ſcarce think what to do but when too late.</l>
                  <l>Or if we think, that fluid thought, like ſeed</l>
                  <l>Rots there to propagate ſome fouler deed.</l>
                  <l>Still we repent and ſin, ſin and repent;</l>
                  <l>We thaw and freeze, we harden and relent.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fires which cool'd to day the morrows heat</l>
                  <l>Rekindles. Thus frail nature does repeat</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:98172:78"/>What ſhe unlearnt, and ſtill by learning on</l>
                  <l>Perfects her leſſon of confuſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sick ſoul! what cure ſhall I for thee deviſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe leprous ſtate corrupts all remedies?</l>
                  <l>What medicine or what cordial can be got</l>
                  <l>For thee, who poyſon'ſt thy beſt antidot?</l>
                  <l>Repentance is thy bane, ſince thou by it</l>
                  <l>Onely reviv'ſt the fault thou didſt commit.</l>
                  <l>Nor griev'ſt thou for the paſt, but art in pain</l>
                  <l>For fear thou mayſt not act it o're again.</l>
                  <l>So that thy tears, like water ſpilt on lime,</l>
                  <l>Serve not to quench, but to advance the crime.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My bleſſed Saviour! unto thee I flie</l>
                  <l>For help againſt this homebred tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt true ſorrows in my ſoul imprint,</l>
                  <l>And draw contrition from a breaſt of flint.</l>
                  <l>Thou canſt reverſe this labyrinth of ſin</l>
                  <l>My wild affects and actions wander in.</l>
                  <l>O guide my faith! and by thy graces clew</l>
                  <l>Teach me to hunt that kingdom at the view</l>
                  <l>Where true joyes reign, which like their day ſhall laſt</l>
                  <l>Thoſe never clouded, nor that overcaſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:98172:79"/>
               <head>Being waked out of my ſleep by a ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff of Candle which offended me, I thus thought.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PEthaps 'twas but conceit. Erroneous ſence!</l>
                  <l>Thou art thine own diſtemper and offence.</l>
                  <l>Imagine then, that ſick unwholſom ſteam</l>
                  <l>Was thy corruption breath'd into a dream.</l>
                  <l>Nor is it ſtrange, when we in charnells dwell,</l>
                  <l>That all our thoughts of earth and frailty ſmell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Man is a Candle, whoſe unhappy light</l>
                  <l>Burns in the day, and ſmothers in the night.</l>
                  <l>And as you ſee the dying taper waſte,</l>
                  <l>By ſuch degrees does he to darkneſs haſte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here is the diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rence: When our bodies lamps</l>
                  <l>Blinded by age, or choakt with mortall damps,</l>
                  <l>Now faint and dim and ſickly 'gin to wink,</l>
                  <l>And in their hollow ſockets lowly ſink;</l>
                  <l>When all our vital fires ceaſing to burn,</l>
                  <l>Leave nought but ſnuff and aſhes in our Urn:</l>
                  <l>God will reſtore thoſe fallen lights again,</l>
                  <l>And kindle them to an Eternal flame.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:98172:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Sic Vita.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIke to the falling of a Starre;</l>
                  <l>Or as the flights of Eagles are;</l>
                  <l>Or like the freſh ſprings gawdy hew;</l>
                  <l>Or ſilver drops of morning dew;</l>
                  <l>Or like a wind that chafes the-flood;</l>
                  <l>Or bubbles which on water ſtood;</l>
                  <l>Even ſuch is man, whoſe borrow'd light</l>
                  <l>Is ſtreight call'd in, and paid to night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Wind blowes out; the Bubble dies;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Spring entomb'd in Autumn lies;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Dew dries up; the Starre is ſhot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Flight is paſt; and Man forgot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:98172:80"/>
               <head>My Midnight Meditation.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ILL buſi'd man! why ſhould'ſt thou take ſuch care</l>
                  <l>To lengthen out thy lifes ſhort Kalendar?</l>
                  <l>When e'ry ſpectacle thou lookſt upon</l>
                  <l>Preſents and acts thy execution.</l>
                  <l>Each drooping ſeaſon and each flower doth cry,</l>
                  <l>Fool! as I fade and wither, thou muſt dy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The beating of thy pulſe (when thou art well)</l>
                  <l>Is juſt the tolling of thy Paſſing Bell:</l>
                  <l>Night is thy Hearſe, whoſe ſable Canopie</l>
                  <l>Covers a like deceaſed day and thee.</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe weeping dewes which nightly fall,</l>
                  <l>Are but the tears ſhed for thy funerall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:98172:80"/>
               <head>A Penitential Hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEarken O God unto a Wretches cryes</l>
                  <l>Who low dejected at thy footſtool lies.</l>
                  <l>Let not the clamour of my heinous ſin</l>
                  <l>Drown my requeſts, which ſtrive to enter in</l>
                  <l>At thoſe bright gates, which alwaies open ſtand</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as beg remiſſion at thy hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Too well I know, if thou in rigour deal</l>
                  <l>I can nor pardon ask, nor yet appeal:</l>
                  <l>To my hoarſe voice, heaven will no audience grant,</l>
                  <l>But deaf as braſs, and hard as adamant</l>
                  <l>Beat back my words; therefore I bring to thee</l>
                  <l>A gracious <hi>Advocate</hi> to plead for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What though my leprous ſoul no <hi>Jordan</hi> can</l>
                  <l>Recure, nor flouds of the lav'd Ocean</l>
                  <l>Make clean? yet from my Saviours bleeding ſide</l>
                  <l>Two large and medicinable rivers glide.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lord,</hi> waſh me where thoſe ſtreams of life abound,</l>
                  <l>And new <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>theſda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> flow from ev'ry wound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:98172:81"/>
                  <l>If I this precious Lather may obtain,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not then deſpair for any ſtain;</l>
                  <l>I need no <hi>Gileads</hi> balm, nor oyl, nor ſhall</l>
                  <l>I for the purifying Hyſſop call:</l>
                  <l>My ſpots will vaniſh in <hi>His</hi> purple flood,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Crimſon</hi> there turn <hi>white,</hi> though waſht with blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See Lord! with broken heart and bended knee,</l>
                  <l>How I addreſs my humble ſuit to Thee;</l>
                  <l>O give that ſuit admittance to thy ears</l>
                  <l>Which floats to thee not in my words but tears:</l>
                  <l>And let my ſinful ſoul this mercy crave</l>
                  <l>Before I fall into the ſilent grave.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:98172:81"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY Occaſioned by ſickneſs.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVEll did the Prophet ask, <hi>Lord what is man?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Implying by the queſtion none can</l>
                  <l>But God reſolve the doubt, much leſs define</l>
                  <l>What Elements this child of duſt combine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Man is a ſtranger to himſelf, and knowes</l>
                  <l>Nothing ſo naturally as his woes.</l>
                  <l>He loves to travel countreys, and confer</l>
                  <l>The ſides of Heavens vaſt Diameter:</l>
                  <l>Delights to ſit in Nile or Boetis lap,</l>
                  <l>Before he hath ſayl'd over his own Map;</l>
                  <l>By which means he returnes, his travel ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Leſs knowing of himſelf then when he went.</l>
                  <l>Who knowledge hunt kept under forrein locks,</l>
                  <l>May bring home wit to hold a Paradox,</l>
                  <l>Yet be fools ſtill. Therefore might I adviſe,</l>
                  <l>I would inform the ſoul before the eyes:</l>
                  <l>Make man into his proper Opticks look,</l>
                  <l>And ſo become the ſtudent and the book</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:98172:82"/>With his conception, his firſt leaf, begin;</l>
                  <l>What is he there but complicated ſin?</l>
                  <l>When riper time, and the approaching birth</l>
                  <l>Ranks him among the creatures of the earth,</l>
                  <l>His wailing mother ſends him forth to greet</l>
                  <l>The light, wrapt in a bloudy winding ſheet;</l>
                  <l>As if he came into the world to crave</l>
                  <l>No place to dwell in, but beſpeak a grave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus like a red and tempeſt-boading morn</l>
                  <l>His dawning is: for being newly born</l>
                  <l>He hayles th'enſuing ſtorm with ſhrieks and cryes,</l>
                  <l>And fines for his admiſſion with wet eyes:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How ſhould that Plant whoſe leaf is bath'd in tear</l>
                  <l>Beat but a bitter fruit in elder years?</l>
                  <l>Juſt ſuch is this, and his maturer age</l>
                  <l>Teems with event more ſad then the preſage.</l>
                  <l>For view him higher, when his childhoods ſpan</l>
                  <l>Is raiſed up to Youths Meridian;</l>
                  <l>When he goes proudly laden with the fruit</l>
                  <l>Which health, or ſtrength, or beauty contribute;</l>
                  <l>Yet as the mounted Canon batters down</l>
                  <l>The Towres and goodly ſtructures of a town:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:98172:82"/>So one ſhort ſickneſs will his force defeat,</l>
                  <l>And his frail Cittadell to rubbiſh beat.</l>
                  <l>How does a dropſie melt him to a floud,</l>
                  <l>Making each vein run water more then bloud?</l>
                  <l>A Chollick wracks him like a Northern guſt,</l>
                  <l>And raging feavers crumble him to duſt.</l>
                  <l>In which unhappy ſtate he is made worſe</l>
                  <l>By his diſeaſes then his makers curſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God</hi> ſaid in <hi>toyl and ſweat</hi> he ſhould earn bread,</l>
                  <l>And without labour not be nouriſhed:</l>
                  <l>Here, though like ropes of falling dew, his ſweat</l>
                  <l>Hangs on his lab'ring brow, he cannot eat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus are his ſins ſcourg'd in oppoſed themes,</l>
                  <l>And luxuries reveng'd by their extremes.</l>
                  <l>He who in health could never be content</l>
                  <l>With Rarities fetcht from each Element,</l>
                  <l>Is now much more afflicted to delight</l>
                  <l>His taſteleſs Palate, and loſt appetite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſides though God ordain'd, that with the light</l>
                  <l>Man ſhould begin his work, yet he made night</l>
                  <l>For his repoſe, in which the weary ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Repaires it ſelf by reſts ſoft recompence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:98172:83"/>But now his watchful nights, and troubled dayes</l>
                  <l>Confuſed heaps of fear and fancy raiſe.</l>
                  <l>His chamber ſeems a looſe and trembling mine;</l>
                  <l>His Pillow quilted with a Porcupine:</l>
                  <l>Pain makes his downy Couch ſharp thornes appear,</l>
                  <l>And ev'ry feather prick him like a ſpear.</l>
                  <l>Thus when all forms of death about him keep,</l>
                  <l>He copies death in any form but ſleep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poor walking-clay! haſt thou a mind to know</l>
                  <l>To what unbleſt beginnings thou doſt ow</l>
                  <l>Thy wretched ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fall ſick a while, and than</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt conceive the pedigree of Man.</l>
                  <l>Learn ſhalt thou from thine own Anatomie,</l>
                  <l>That earth his mother, wormes his ſiſters be.</l>
                  <l>That he's a ſhort-liv'd vapour upward wrought,</l>
                  <l>And by corruption unto nothing brought.</l>
                  <l>A ſtagg'ring Meteor by croſs Planets bear,</l>
                  <l>Which often reeles and falles before his ſet:</l>
                  <l>A tree which withers faſter then it growes;</l>
                  <l>A torch puff't out by ev'ry wind that blowes;</l>
                  <l>A web of fourty weekes ſpun forth in pain,</l>
                  <l>And in a moment ravell'd out again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:98172:83"/>
                  <l>This is the Model of frail man: Then ſay</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat his duration's onely for a day:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd in that day more fies of changes paſs,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen Atomes run in the turn'd Hower-glaſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So that th'inceſſant cares which life invade</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight for ſtrong truth their hereſie perſwade,</l>
                  <l>Who did maintain that humane ſoules are ſent</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to the body for their puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> leaſt with that Greek Sage ſtill make us cry,</l>
                  <l>Not to be born, or being born to dy.<note n="*" place="margin">Non na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſci, aut quàm ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſinè mori.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But Faith ſteers up to a more glorious ſcope,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich ſweetens our ſharp paſſage; and firm hope</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hors our torne Barks on a bleſſed ſhore,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yond the Dead ſea we here ferry o're.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this, Death is our Pilot, and diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Agent which ſolicites our releaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though croſſes then poure on my reſtleſs head,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> lingring ſickneſs nail me to my bed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t this my Thoughts eternall comfort bee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at my clos'd eyes a better light ſhall ſee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:98172:84"/>And when by fortunes or by natures ſtroke</l>
                  <l>My bodies earthen Pitcher muſt be broke,</l>
                  <l>My Soul, like Gideons lamp, from her crackt urn</l>
                  <l>Shall Deaths black night to endleſſe luſtre turn.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:98172:84"/>
               <head>The Dirge.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHat is th'Exiſtence of Mans life?</l>
                  <l>But open war, or ſlumber'd ſtrife.</l>
                  <l>Where ſickneſs to his ſenſe preſents</l>
                  <l>The combat of the Elements:</l>
                  <l>And never feels a perfect Peace</l>
                  <l>Till deaths cold hand ſigns his releaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is a ſtorm where the hot blood</l>
                  <l>Out-vies in rage the boyling flood;</l>
                  <l>And each loud Paſſion of the mind</l>
                  <l>Is like a furious guſt of wind,</l>
                  <l>Which beats his Bark with many a Wave</l>
                  <l>Till he caſts Anchor in the Grave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is a flower which buds and growes,</l>
                  <l>And withers as the leaves diſcloſe;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſpring and fall faint ſeaſons keep,</l>
                  <l>Like fits of waking before ſleep:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhrinks into that fatal mold</l>
                  <l>Where its firſt being was enroll'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:98172:85"/>
                  <l>It is a dream, whoſe ſeeming truth</l>
                  <l>Is moraliz'd in age and youth:</l>
                  <l>Where all the comforts he can ſhare</l>
                  <l>As wandring as his fancies are;</l>
                  <l>Till in a miſt of dark decay</l>
                  <l>The dreamer vaniſh quire away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is a Diall, which points out</l>
                  <l>The Sun-ſet as it moves about:</l>
                  <l>And ſhadowes out in lines of night</l>
                  <l>The ſubtile ſtages of times ſlight,</l>
                  <l>Till all obſcuring earth hath laid</l>
                  <l>The body in perpetual ſhade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is a weary enterlude</l>
                  <l>Which doth ſhort joyes, long woes include.</l>
                  <l>The World the Stage, the Prologue tears,</l>
                  <l>The Acts vain hope, and vary'd fears:</l>
                  <l>The Scene ſhuts up with loſs of breath,</l>
                  <l>And leaves no Epilogue but Death.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:98172:85"/>
               <head>AN ELEGY Occaſioned by the leſſe of the moſt incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lady Stanhope, daught or to the Earl of Northumberland.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LIghtned by that dimme Torch our ſorrow bear,</l>
                  <l>We ſadly trace thy Coffin with our rears;</l>
                  <l>And though the Ceremonious Rites are paſt</l>
                  <l>Since thy fair body into earth was caſt;</l>
                  <l>Though all thy Hatchments into ragges are come,</l>
                  <l>Thy Funerall Robes and Ornaments outwom;</l>
                  <l>We ſtill thy mourners without Shew or Art,</l>
                  <l>With ſolemn Blacks hung round about our heart,</l>
                  <l>Thus conſtantly the Obſequies renew</l>
                  <l>Which to thy precious memory are due.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet think not that we tudely would invade</l>
                  <l>The dark receſs of thine untroubled ſhade,</l>
                  <l>Or give diſturbance to that happy peace</l>
                  <l>Which thou enjoy'ſt at full ſince thy releaſe;</l>
                  <l>Much leſs in ſullen murmurs do complain</l>
                  <l>Of His decree who took thee back again,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:98172:86"/>And did e're Fame had ſpread thy vertues light,</l>
                  <l>Eclipſe and fold thee up in endleſs night.</l>
                  <l>This like an act of envy not of grief</l>
                  <l>Might doubt thy bliſs, and ſhake our own belief,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtudi'd wiſhes no proportion bear</l>
                  <l>With joyes which crown thee now in glories ſphere.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Know then bleſt Soul! we for our ſelves not thee</l>
                  <l>Seal our woes dictate by this Elegie:</l>
                  <l>Wherein our tears united in one ſtreame</l>
                  <l>Shall to ſucceeding times convey this theme,</l>
                  <l>Worth all mens pity who diſcern how rare</l>
                  <l>Such early growths of fame and goodneſs are.</l>
                  <l>Of theſe part muſt thy ſexes loſs bewail</l>
                  <l>Maim'd in her nobleſt Patterns through thy fail;</l>
                  <l>For 'twould require a double term of life</l>
                  <l>To match thee as a daughter or a wife:</l>
                  <l>Both which Northumberlands dear loſs improve</l>
                  <l>And make his ſorrow equal to his love.</l>
                  <l>The reſt fall for our ſelves, who caſt behind</l>
                  <l>Cannot yet reach the Peace which thou doſt find;</l>
                  <l>But ſlowly follow thee in that dull ſtage</l>
                  <l>Which moſt untimely poaſted hence thy age.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:98172:86"/>
                  <l>Thus like religious Pilgrims who deſigne</l>
                  <l>A ſhort ſalute to their beloved Shrine,</l>
                  <l>Moſt ſad and humble Votaries we come</l>
                  <l>To offer up our ſighs upon thy Tomb,</l>
                  <l>And wet thy Marble with our dropping eyes</l>
                  <l>Which till the ſpring which feeds their current dries</l>
                  <l>Reſolve each falling night and riſing day</l>
                  <l>This mournfull homage at thy Grave to pay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>PAge</hi> 2. The Pink never wrote by the Author of theſe Poems. <hi>Pag.</hi> 22. <hi>lin.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> ſhe <hi>read</hi> air.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 100. <hi>lin.</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> Mattox <hi>read</hi> Mattocks.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98172:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
